You're tired — I know.
This isn't something you have to listen
to, it's just something to fall asleep in.
The whole Gospel of Luke, read slowly, and
then Ecclesiastes.
Close your eyes.
If you'd like something carried in prayer
tonight, leave it in the comments.
Subscribe if these readings help you
sleep.
Lord, you know how long this stretch has
been.
Not one bad day — a run of
them, close enough together that I've stopped counting.
I keep waiting for the week that
finally feels different, and it keeps not arriving.
I'm not asking you to explain the season
I'm in.
Ecclesiastes says there is a time for
everything, and I believe it, though I'd rather
be past this particular time than in the
middle of it.
What I need tonight is smaller than an
answer.
I need to stop straining for a while.
So let Luke's account of your Son go past
me slowly — the long walk of it, the
meals, the people he stopped for.
He was never in a hurry.
Let some of that reach me.
Take the ache out of my shoulders.
Take the argument out of my head.
Let me sleep the way a child sleeps in
a house where someone else is awake and keeping
watch.
And be gentle tonight with everyone else
who has run out of ways to fix things.
Amen.
Luke, chapter one.
Since many have undertaken to set in order
a narrative concerning those matters which
have been fulfilled amongst us, even as
those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses
and servants of the word delivered them to
us, it seemed good to me also, having traced
the course of all things accurately from the
first, to write to you in order, most excellent
Theophilus; that you might know the certainty
concerning the things in which you were
instructed.
There was in the days of Herod, the
king of Judea, a certain priest named Zacharias,
of the priestly division of Abijah.
He had a wife of the daughters of Aaron,
and her name was Elizabeth.
They were both righteous before God,
walking blamelessly in all the commandments and
ordinances of the Lord.
But they had no child, because Elizabeth
was barren, and they both were well advanced
in years.
Now while he executed the priest’s office before
God in the order of his division according
to the custom of the priest’s office, his lot
was to enter into the temple of the Lord
and burn incense.
The whole multitude of the people were
praying outside at the hour of incense.
An angel of the Lord appeared to him, standing
on the right side of the altar of incense.
Zacharias was troubled when he saw him,
and fear fell upon him.
But the angel said to him, “Don’t
be afraid, Zacharias, because your request has been
heard.
Your wife, Elizabeth, will bear you a son,
and you shall call his name John.
You will have joy and gladness, and many
will rejoice at his birth.
For he will be great in the sight of the
Lord, and he will drink no wine nor strong drink.
He will be filled with the Holy Spirit,
even from his mother’s womb.
He will turn many of the children of
Israel to the Lord their God.
He will go before him in the spirit and
power of Elijah, ‘to turn the hearts of the fathers
to the children,’ and the disobedient to the
wisdom of the just; to prepare a people
prepared for the Lord.”
Zacharias said to the angel, “How can I be
sure of this?
For I am an old man, and my wife is well
advanced in years.”
The angel answered him, “I am Gabriel, who
stands in the presence of God.
I was sent to speak to you and to bring
you this good news.
Behold, you will be silent and not able to
speak until the day that these things will
happen, because you didn’t believe my words,
which will be fulfilled in their proper
time.”
The people were waiting for Zacharias, and
they marvelled that he delayed in the temple.
When he came out, he could not speak to
them.
They perceived that he had seen a vision
in the temple.
He continued making signs to them, and
remained mute.
When the days of his service were
fulfilled, he departed to his house.
After these days Elizabeth his wife conceived,
and she hid herself five months, saying,
“Thus has the Lord done to me in the days
in which he looked at me, to take away my reproach
amongst men.”
Now in the sixth month, the angel Gabriel was
sent from God to a city of Galilee named
Nazareth, to a virgin pledged to be married
to a man whose name was Joseph, of David’s
house.
The virgin’s name was Mary.
Having come in, the angel said to her,
“Rejoice, you highly favoured one!
The Lord is with you.
Blessed are you amongst women!”
But when she saw him, she was greatly
troubled at the saying, and considered what kind
of salutation this might be.
The angel said to her, “Don’t be afraid,
Mary, for you have found favour with God.
Behold, you will conceive in your womb and give
birth to a son, and shall name him ‘Jesus.’
He will be great and will be called the
Son of the Most High.
The Lord God will give him the throne of
his father David, and he will reign over the
house of Jacob forever.
There will be no end to his Kingdom.”
Mary said to the angel, “How can this be,
seeing I am a virgin?”
The angel answered her, “The Holy Spirit will
come on you, and the power of the Most
High will overshadow you.
Therefore also the holy one who is born
from you will be called the Son of God.
Behold, Elizabeth your relative also has
conceived a son in her old age; and
this is the sixth month with her who was
called barren.
For nothing spoken by God is impossible.”
Mary said, “Behold, the servant of the
Lord; let it be done to me according to
your word.”
Then the angel departed from her.
Mary arose in those days and went into the
hill country with haste, into a city of Judah,
and entered into the house of Zacharias
and greeted Elizabeth.
When Elizabeth heard Mary’s greeting, the baby
leapt in her womb; and Elizabeth was filled
with the Holy Spirit.
She called out with a loud voice and
said, “Blessed are you amongst women, and blessed
is the fruit of your womb!
Why am I so favoured, that the mother of
my Lord should come to me?
For behold, when the voice of your greeting came
into my ears, the baby leapt in my womb
for joy!
Blessed is she who believed, for there will
be a fulfilment of the things which have
been spoken to her from the Lord!”
Mary said, “My soul magnifies the Lord.
My spirit has rejoiced in God my Saviour, for
he has looked at the humble state of his
servant.
For behold, from now on, all generations
will call me blessed.
For he who is mighty has done great things
for me.
Holy is his name.
His mercy is for generations and
generations on those who fear him.
He has shown strength with his arm.
He has scattered the proud in the
imagination of their hearts.
He has put down princes from their
thrones, and has exalted the lowly.
He has filled the hungry with good things.
He has sent the rich away empty.
He has given help to Israel, his servant,
that he might remember mercy, as he spoke to
our fathers, to Abraham and his offspring
forever.”
Mary stayed with her about three months,
and then returned to her house.
Now the time that Elizabeth should give birth
was fulfilled, and she gave birth to a
son.
Her neighbours and her relatives heard that
the Lord had magnified his mercy towards
her, and they rejoiced with her.
On the eighth day, they came to circumcise
the child; and they would have called him
Zacharias, after the name of his father.
His mother answered, “Not so; but he will
be called John.”
They said to her, “There is no one
amongst your relatives who is called by this name.”
They made signs to his father, what he
would have him called.
He asked for a writing tablet, and wrote,
“His name is John.”
They all marvelled.
His mouth was opened immediately and his
tongue freed, and he spoke, blessing God.
Fear came on all who lived around them,
and all these sayings were talked about throughout
all the hill country of Judea.
All who heard them laid them up in
their heart, saying, “What then will this child be?”
The hand of the Lord was with him.
His father Zacharias was filled with
the Holy Spirit, and prophesied, saying, “Blessed
be the Lord, the God of Israel, for he has
visited and redeemed his people; and
has raised up a horn of salvation for us
in the house of his servant David (as he spoke
by the mouth of his holy prophets who
have been from of old), salvation from our enemies
and from the hand of all who hate
us; to show mercy towards our fathers, to remember
his holy covenant, the oath which he swore
to Abraham our father, to grant to
us that we, being delivered out of the
hand of our enemies, should serve him without
fear, in holiness and righteousness before
him all the days of our life.
And you, child, will be called a prophet of
the Most High; for you will go before the
face of the Lord to prepare his ways,
to give knowledge of salvation to his people by
the remission of their sins, because of the
tender mercy of our God, by which the dawn
from on high will visit us, to shine on
those who sit in darkness and the shadow of death;
to guide our feet into the way of peace.”
The child was growing and becoming strong
in spirit, and was in the desert until the
day of his public appearance to Israel.
Luke, chapter two.
Now in those days, a decree went out
from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be
enrolled.
This was the first enrolment made when
Quirinius was governor of Syria.
All went to enrol themselves, everyone to
his own city.
Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of
the city of Nazareth, into Judea, to
David’s city, which is called Bethlehem, because he
was of the house and family of David,
to enrol himself with Mary, who was pledged
to be married to him as wife, being pregnant.
While they were there, the day had come
for her to give birth.
She gave birth to her firstborn son.
She wrapped him in bands of cloth and laid
him in a feeding trough, because there was
no room for them in the inn.
There were shepherds in the same country staying
in the field, and keeping watch by night
over their flock.
Behold, an angel of the Lord stood by them,
and the glory of the Lord shone around them,
and they were terrified.
The angel said to them, “Don’t be afraid,
for behold, I bring you good news of great
joy which will be to all the people.
For there is born to you today, in David’s
city, a Saviour, who is Christ the Lord.
This is the sign to you: you will find a
baby wrapped in strips of cloth, lying in
a feeding trough.”
Suddenly, there was with the angel a
multitude of the heavenly army praising God and
saying, “Glory to God in the highest, on
earth peace, good will towards men.”
When the angels went away from them into
the sky, the shepherds said to one another,
“Let’s go to Bethlehem, now, and see this
thing that has happened, which the Lord has
made known to us.”
They came with haste and found both Mary and
Joseph, and the baby was lying in the feeding
trough.
When they saw it, they publicised widely the
saying which was spoken to them about this
child.
All who heard it wondered at the things
which were spoken to them by the shepherds.
But Mary kept all these sayings, pondering
them in her heart.
The shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God
for all the things that they had
heard and seen, just as it was told them.
When eight days were fulfilled for the
circumcision of the child, his name was called
Jesus, which was given by the angel before
he was conceived in the womb.
When the days of their purification according
to the law of Moses were fulfilled, they
brought him up to Jerusalem to present him to
the Lord (as it is written in the law of
the Lord, “Every male who opens the womb shall
be called holy to the Lord”), and to offer
a sacrifice according to that which is said in
the law of the Lord, “A pair of turtledoves,
or two young pigeons.”
Behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose
name was Simeon.
This man was righteous and devout, looking
for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy
Spirit was on him.
It had been revealed to him by the Holy
Spirit that he should not see death before he
had seen the Lord’s Christ.
He came in the Spirit into the temple.
When the parents brought in the child,
Jesus, that they might do concerning him according
to the custom of the law, then he received
him into his arms and blessed God, and
said, “Now you are releasing your servant,
Master, according to your word, in peace;
for my eyes have seen your salvation, which
you have prepared before the face of all
peoples; a light for revelation to the
nations, and the glory of your people Israel.”
Joseph and his mother were marvelling at
the things which were spoken concerning him.
Simeon blessed them, and said to Mary,
his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for
the falling and the rising of many in
Israel, and for a sign which is spoken against.
Yes, a sword will pierce through your own
soul, that the thoughts of many hearts may
be revealed.”
There was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter
of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher (she
was of a great age, having lived with
a husband seven years from her virginity, and she
had been a widow for about eighty-four
years), who didn’t depart from the temple, worshipping
with fastings and petitions night and day.
Coming up at that very hour, she gave thanks
to the Lord, and spoke of him to all those
who were looking for redemption in
Jerusalem.
When they had accomplished all things that were
according to the law of the Lord, they
returned into Galilee, to their own city,
Nazareth.
The child was growing, and was becoming
strong in spirit, being filled with wisdom, and
the grace of God was upon him.
His parents went every year to Jerusalem
at the feast of the Passover.
When he was twelve years old, they went
up to Jerusalem according to the custom of the
feast; and when they had fulfilled the days,
as they were returning, the boy Jesus stayed
behind in Jerusalem.
Joseph and his mother didn’t know it, but
supposing him to be in the company, they went
a day’s journey; and they looked for him
amongst their relatives and acquaintances.
When they didn’t find him, they returned
to Jerusalem, looking for him.
After three days they found him in the
temple, sitting in the middle of the teachers,
both listening to them and asking them
questions.
All who heard him were amazed at his
understanding and his answers.
When they saw him, they were astonished;
and his mother said to him, “Son, why have
you treated us this way?
Behold, your father and I were anxiously
looking for you.”
He said to them, “Why were you looking for
me?
Didn’t you know that I must be in my
Father’s house?”
They didn’t understand the saying which he
spoke to them.
And he went down with them and came to
Nazareth.
He was subject to them, and his mother
kept all these sayings in her heart.
And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature,
and in favour with God and men.
Luke, chapter three.
Now in the fifteenth year of the
reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor
of Judea, and Herod being tetrarch of
Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of the
region of Ituraea and Trachonitis, and
Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene, during the high
priesthood of Annas and Caiaphas, the word
of God came to John, the son of Zacharias,
in the wilderness.
He came into all the region around
the Jordan, preaching the baptism of repentance for
remission of sins.
As it is written in the book of the
words of Isaiah the prophet, “The voice of one crying
in the wilderness, ‘Make ready the way of
the Lord.
Make his paths straight.
Every valley will be filled.
Every mountain and hill will be brought
low.
The crooked will become straight, and the
rough ways smooth.
All flesh will see God’s salvation.’” He
said therefore to the multitudes who went out
to be baptised by him, “You offspring of
vipers, who warned you to flee from the wrath
to come?
Therefore produce fruits worthy of repentance,
and don’t begin to say amongst yourselves,
‘We have Abraham for our father;’ for I tell
you that God is able to raise up children
to Abraham from these stones!
Even now the axe also lies at the root of
the trees.
Every tree therefore that doesn’t produce
good fruit is cut down and thrown into the
fire.”
The multitudes asked him, “What then must
we do?”
He answered them, “He who has two coats,
let him give to him who has none.
He who has food, let him do likewise.”
Tax collectors also came to be baptised, and
they said to him, “Teacher, what must we
do?”
He said to them, “Collect no more than
that which is appointed to you.”
Soldiers also asked him, saying, “What
about us?
What must we do?”
He said to them, “Extort from no
one by violence, neither accuse anyone wrongfully.
Be content with your wages.”
As the people were in expectation, and
all men reasoned in their hearts concerning John,
whether perhaps he was the Christ, John
answered them all, “I indeed baptise
you with water, but he comes who is mightier
than I, the strap of whose sandals I am
not worthy to loosen.
He will baptise you in the Holy Spirit and
fire.
His winnowing fan is in his hand,
and he will thoroughly cleanse his threshing floor,
and will gather the wheat into his barn;
but he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable
fire.”
Then with many other exhortations he preached
good news to the people, but Herod the
tetrarch, being reproved by him for Herodias,
his brother’s wife, and for all the evil
things which Herod had done, added this
also to them all, that he shut up John in
prison.
Now when all the people were baptised,
Jesus also had been baptised and was praying.
The sky was opened, and the Holy Spirit descended
in a bodily form like a dove on him;
and a voice came out of the sky, saying
“You are my beloved Son.
In you I am well pleased.”
Jesus himself, when he began to teach, was
about thirty years old, being
the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the
son of Heli, the son of Matthat,
the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the
son of Jannai, the son of Joseph, the son
of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of
Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai,
the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the
son of Semein, the son of Joseph, the son
of Judah, the son of Joanan, the son of
Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel,
the son of Neri, the son of Melchi, the son
of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmodam,
the son of Er, the son of Jose, the son
of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat,
the son of Levi, the son of Simeon, the son
of Judah, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonan,
the son of Eliakim, the son of Melea, the
son of Menan, the son of Mattatha, the son
of Nathan, the son of David, the son of
Jesse, the son of Obed, the son of Boaz, the
son of Salmon, the son of Nahshon, the son
of Amminadab, the son of Aram, the son of
Hezron, the son of Perez, the son of Judah,
the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son
of Abraham, the son of Terah, the son of
Nahor, the son of Serug, the son of Reu, the
son of Peleg, the son of Eber, the son
of Shelah, the son of Cainan, the son of Arphaxad,
the son of Shem, the son of Noah, the
son of Lamech, the son of Methuselah, the son of
Enoch, the son of Jared, the son of Mahalaleel,
the son of Cainan, the son of Enos, the
son of Seth, the son of Adam, the son of
God.
Luke, chapter four.
Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from
the Jordan and was led by the Spirit into
the wilderness for forty days, being
tempted by the devil.
He ate nothing in those days.
Afterward, when they were completed, he
was hungry.
The devil said to him, “If you are the
Son of God, command this stone to become bread.”
Jesus answered him, saying, “It is written, ‘Man
shall not live by bread alone, but by
every word of God.’” The devil, leading him
up on a high mountain, showed him all the
kingdoms of the world in a moment of time.
The devil said to him, “I will give you
all this authority and their glory, for it
has been delivered to me, and I give it to
whomever I want.
If you therefore will worship before me,
it will all be yours.”
Jesus answered him, “Get behind me, Satan!
For it is written, ‘You shall worship the
Lord your God, and you shall serve him only.’”
He led him to Jerusalem and set him on
the pinnacle of the temple, and said to him, “If
you are the Son of God, cast yourself down
from here, for it is written, ‘He will put
his angels in charge of you, to guard you;’
and, ‘On their hands they will bear you up,
lest perhaps you dash your foot against a
stone.’” Jesus answering, said to him, “It
has been said, ‘You shall not tempt the
Lord your God.’” When the devil had completed
every temptation, he departed from him
until another time.
Jesus returned in the power of the Spirit
into Galilee, and news about him spread through
all the surrounding area.
He taught in their synagogues, being
glorified by all.
He came to Nazareth, where he had been
brought up.
He entered, as was his custom, into the
synagogue on the Sabbath day, and stood up to
read.
The book of the prophet Isaiah was handed
to him.
He opened the book, and found the place
where it was written, “The Spirit of the Lord
is on me, because he has anointed me to
preach good news to the poor.
He has sent me to heal the broken
hearted, to proclaim release to the captives, recovering
of sight to the blind, to deliver those
who are crushed, and to proclaim the acceptable
year of the Lord.”
He closed the book, gave it back to the
attendant, and sat down.
The eyes of all in the synagogue were
fastened on him.
He began to tell them, “Today, this
Scripture has been fulfilled in your hearing.”
All testified about him and wondered at
the gracious words which proceeded out of his
mouth; and they said, “Isn’t this Joseph’s
son?”
He said to them, “Doubtless you will
tell me this proverb, ‘Physician, heal yourself!
Whatever we have heard done at Capernaum,
do also here in your hometown.’” He said,
“Most certainly I tell you, no prophet is
acceptable in his hometown.
But truly I tell you, there were many widows
in Israel in the days of Elijah, when the
sky was shut up three years and six months,
when a great famine came over all the land.
Elijah was sent to none of them, except to
Zarephath, in the land of Sidon, to a woman
who was a widow.
There were many lepers in Israel in the time
of Elisha the prophet, yet not one of them
was cleansed, except Naaman, the Syrian.”
They were all filled with wrath in the
synagogue as they heard these things.
They rose up, threw him out of the city, and
led him to the brow of the hill that their
city was built on, that they might throw
him off the cliff.
But he, passing through the middle of
them, went his way.
He came down to Capernaum, a city of
Galilee.
He was teaching them on the Sabbath day,
and they were astonished at his teaching, for
his word was with authority.
In the synagogue there was a man who had
a spirit of an unclean demon; and he cried out
with a loud voice, saying, “Ah!
what have we to do with you, Jesus of
Nazareth?
Have you come to destroy us?
I know who you are: the Holy One of God!”
Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silent and
come out of him!”
When the demon had thrown him down in the
middle of them, he came out of him, having
done him no harm.
Amazement came on all and they spoke
together, one with another, saying, “What is
this word?
For with authority and power he commands
the unclean spirits, and they come out!”
News about him went out into every place
of the surrounding region.
He rose up from the synagogue and entered
into Simon’s house.
Simon’s mother-in-law was afflicted with a great
fever, and they begged him to help her.
He stood over her and rebuked the fever,
and it left her.
Immediately she rose up and served them.
When the sun was setting, all those who
had any sick with various diseases brought them
to him; and he laid his hands on every one
of them, and healed them.
Demons also came out of many, crying out
and saying, “You are the Christ, the Son
of God!”
Rebuking them, he didn’t allow them to speak,
because they knew that he was the Christ.
When it was day, he departed and went
into an uninhabited place and the multitudes looked
for him, and came to him, and held on
to him, so that he wouldn’t go away from them.
But he said to them, “I must preach the
good news of God’s Kingdom to the other cities
also.
For this reason I have been sent.”
He was preaching in the synagogues of
Galilee.
Luke, chapter five.
Now while the multitude pressed on him and
heard the word of God, he was standing by
the lake of Gennesaret.
He saw two boats standing by the lake, but
the fishermen had gone out of them and were
washing their nets.
He entered into one of the boats, which was
Simon’s, and asked him to put out a little
from the land.
He sat down and taught the multitudes from
the boat.
When he had finished speaking, he said to
Simon, “Put out into the deep and let down
your nets for a catch.”
Simon answered him, “Master, we worked all
night and caught nothing; but
at your word I will let down the net.”
When they had done this, they caught a
great multitude of fish, and their net was breaking.
They beckoned to their partners in the other
boat, that they should come and help them.
They came and filled both boats, so that
they began to sink.
But Simon Peter, when he saw it, fell down
at Jesus’ knees, saying, “Depart
from me, for I am a sinful man, Lord.”
For he was amazed, and all who were with
him, at the catch of fish which they had caught;
and so also were James and John, sons of
Zebedee, who were partners with Simon.
Jesus said to Simon, “Don’t be afraid.
From now on you will be catching people
alive.”
When they had brought their boats to land,
they left everything, and followed him.
While he was in one of the cities, behold,
there was a man full of leprosy.
When he saw Jesus, he fell on his face and
begged him, saying, “Lord, if you want to,
you can make me clean.”
He stretched out his hand and touched him,
saying, “I want to.
Be made clean.”
Immediately the leprosy left him.
He commanded him to tell no one, “But go
your way and show yourself to the priest, and
offer for your cleansing according to what
Moses commanded, for a testimony to them.”
But the report concerning him spread much
more, and great multitudes came together to
hear and to be healed by him of their
infirmities.
But he withdrew himself into the desert
and prayed.
On one of those days, he was teaching;
and there were Pharisees and teachers of the law
sitting by who had come out of every
village of Galilee, Judea, and Jerusalem.
The power of the Lord was with him to heal
them.
Behold, men brought a paralysed man on a cot,
and they sought to bring him in to lay
before Jesus.
Not finding a way to bring him in because
of the multitude, they went up to the housetop
and let him down through the tiles with
his cot into the middle before Jesus.
Seeing their faith, he said to him, “Man,
your sins are forgiven you.”
The scribes and the Pharisees began to
reason, saying, “Who is this who speaks blasphemies?
Who can forgive sins, but God alone?”
But Jesus, perceiving their thoughts, answered them,
“Why are you reasoning so in your
hearts?
Which is easier to say, ‘Your sins are
forgiven you,’ or to say, ‘Arise and walk?’
But that you may know that the Son of
Man has authority on earth to forgive sins,” he
said to the paralysed man, “I tell you,
arise, take up your cot, and go to
your house.”
Immediately he rose up before them, and took
up that which he was laying on, and departed
to his house, glorifying God.
Amazement took hold on all, and they
glorified God.
They were filled with fear, saying, “We
have seen strange things today.”
After these things he went out and saw
a tax collector named Levi sitting at the tax
office, and said to him, “Follow me!”
He left everything, and rose up and
followed him.
Levi made a great feast for him in his
house.
There was a great crowd of tax collectors
and others who were reclining with them.
Their scribes and the Pharisees murmured against
his disciples, saying, “Why do you eat
and drink with the tax collectors and
sinners?”
Jesus answered them, “Those who are healthy have
no need for a physician, but those who
are sick do.
I have not come to call the righteous, but
sinners, to repentance.”
They said to him, “Why do John’s disciples
often fast and pray, likewise also
the disciples of the Pharisees, but yours
eat and drink?”
He said to them, “Can you make the
friends of the bridegroom fast while the bridegroom
is with them?
But the days will come when the bridegroom
will be taken away from them.
Then they will fast in those days.”
He also told a parable to them.
“No one puts a piece from a new garment on
an old garment, or else he will tear the new,
and also the piece from the new will not
match the old.
No one puts new wine into old wine skins,
or else the new wine will burst the skins,
and it will be spilled and the skins will
be destroyed.
But new wine must be put into fresh wine
skins, and both are preserved.
No man having drunk old wine immediately
desires new, for he says, ‘The
old is better.’” Luke, chapter six.
Now on the second Sabbath after the first,
he was going through the grain fields.
His disciples plucked the heads of grain
and ate, rubbing them in their hands.
But some of the Pharisees said to them, “Why
do you do that which is not lawful to do
on the Sabbath day?”
Jesus, answering them, said, “Haven’t you
read what David did when he was hungry, he
and those who were with him, how he entered
into God’s house, and took and ate the show
bread, and gave also to those who were with
him, which is not lawful to eat except for
the priests alone?”
He said to them, “The Son of Man is lord
of the Sabbath.”
It also happened on another Sabbath that
he entered into the synagogue and taught.
There was a man there, and his right hand
was withered.
The scribes and the Pharisees watched him, to
see whether he would heal on the Sabbath,
that they might find an accusation against
him.
But he knew their thoughts; and he said to
the man who had the withered hand, “Rise up
and stand in the middle.”
He arose and stood.
Then Jesus said to them, “I will ask you
something: Is it lawful on the Sabbath to do
good, or to do harm?
To save a life, or to kill?”
He looked around at them all, and said to
the man, “Stretch out your hand.”
He did, and his hand was restored as sound
as the other.
But they were filled with rage, and talked
with one another about what they might do
to Jesus.
In these days, he went out to the mountain
to pray, and he continued all night
in prayer to God.
When it was day, he called his disciples,
and from them he chose twelve, whom he also
named apostles: Simon, whom he also named
Peter; Andrew, his
brother; James; John; Philip; Bartholomew;
Matthew; Thomas;
James the son of Alphaeus; Simon who was
called the Zealot; Judas the son of James;
and Judas Iscariot, who also became a
traitor.
He came down with them and stood on a
level place, with a crowd of his disciples and
a great number of the people from all Judea
and Jerusalem and the sea coast of Tyre and
Sidon, who came to hear him and to be
healed of their diseases, as well as those who
were troubled by unclean spirits; and they
were being healed.
All the multitude sought to touch him, for
power came out of him and healed them all.
He lifted up his eyes to his disciples,
and said: “Blessed are you who are poor, for
God’s Kingdom is yours.
Blessed are you who hunger now, for you
will be filled.
Blessed are you who weep now, for you will
laugh.
Blessed are you when men hate you, and
when they exclude and mock you, and throw out
your name as evil, for the Son of Man’s
sake.
Rejoice in that day and leap for joy, for
behold, your reward is great in heaven,
for their fathers did the same thing to
the prophets.
“But woe to you who are rich!
For you have received your consolation.
Woe to you, you who are full now, for you
will be hungry.
Woe to you who laugh now, for you will
mourn and weep.
Woe, when men speak well of you, for their
fathers did the same thing to the false prophets.
“But I tell you who hear: love your enemies,
do good to those who hate you, bless those
who curse you, and pray for those who
mistreat you.
To him who strikes you on the cheek, offer
also the other; and from him who takes away
your cloak, don’t withhold your coat also.
Give to everyone who asks you, and don’t ask
him who takes away your goods to give them
back again.
“As you would like people to do to you, do
exactly so to them.
“If you love those who love you, what
credit is that to you?
For even sinners love those who love them.
If you do good to those who do good to
you, what credit is that to you?
For even sinners do the same.
If you lend to those from whom you hope to
receive, what credit is that to you?
Even sinners lend to sinners, to receive
back as much.
But love your enemies, and do good, and
lend, expecting nothing back; and
your reward will be great, and you will be
children of the Most High; for he is kind
towards the unthankful and evil.
“Therefore be merciful, even as your
Father is also merciful.
Don’t judge, and you won’t be judged.
Don’t condemn, and you won’t be condemned.
Set free, and you will be set free.
“Give, and it will be given to
you: good measure, pressed down, shaken together, and
running over, will be given to you.
For with the same measure you measure it
will be measured back to you.”
He spoke a parable to them.
“Can the blind guide the blind?
Won’t they both fall into a pit?
A disciple is not above his teacher, but
everyone when he is fully trained will be like
his teacher.
Why do you see the speck of chaff that
is in your brother’s eye, but don’t consider the
beam that is in your own eye?
Or how can you tell your brother, ‘Brother,
let me remove the speck of chaff that is
in your eye,’ when you yourself don’t see
the beam that is in your own eye?
You hypocrite!
First remove the beam from your own eye, and
then you can see clearly to remove the speck
of chaff that is in your brother’s eye.
“For there is no good tree that produces
rotten fruit, nor again a rotten tree that produces
good fruit.
For each tree is known by its own fruit.
For people don’t gather figs from thorns, nor
do they gather grapes from a bramble bush.
The good man out of the good treasure of
his heart brings out that which is good, and
the evil man out of the evil treasure of
his heart brings out that which is evil, for
out of the abundance of the heart, his
mouth speaks.
“Why do you call me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ and
don’t do the things which I say?
Everyone who comes to me, and hears my words
and does them, I will show you who he is
like.
He is like a man building a house, who dug
and went deep and laid a foundation on
the rock.
When a flood arose, the stream broke against
that house, and could not shake it, because
it was founded on the rock.
But he who hears and doesn’t do, is like a
man who built a house on the earth without
a foundation, against which the stream broke,
and immediately it fell; and the ruin of
that house was great.”
Luke, chapter seven.
After he had finished speaking in the
hearing of the people, he entered into Capernaum.
A certain centurion’s servant, who was dear to
him, was sick and at the point of death.
When he heard about Jesus, he sent to him
elders of the Jews, asking him to come and
save his servant.
When they came to Jesus, they begged him
earnestly, saying, “He is worthy for you to
do this for him, for he loves our nation,
and he built our synagogue for us.”
Jesus went with them.
When he was now not far from the
house, the centurion sent friends to him, saying to
him, “Lord, don’t trouble yourself, for I am
not worthy for you to come under my roof.
Therefore I didn’t even think myself worthy to
come to you; but say the word, and my
servant will be healed.
For I also am a man placed under
authority, having under myself soldiers.
I tell this one, ‘Go!’
and he goes; and to another, ‘Come!’
and he comes; and to my servant, ‘Do
this,’ and he does it.”
When Jesus heard these things, he marvelled at
him, and turned and said to the multitude
who followed him, “I tell you, I have not
found such great faith, no,
not in Israel.”
Those who were sent, returning to the house,
found that the servant who had been sick
was well.
Soon afterwards, he went to a city called
Nain.
Many of his disciples, along with a great
multitude, went with him.
Now when he came near to the gate of
the city, behold, one who was dead was carried out,
the only born son of his mother, and she
was a widow.
Many people of the city were with her.
When the Lord saw her, he had compassion
on her and said to her, “Don’t cry.”
He came near and touched the coffin, and
the bearers stood still.
He said, “Young man, I tell you, arise!”
He who was dead sat up and began to speak.
Then he gave him to his mother.
Fear took hold of all, and they glorified
God, saying, “A great prophet has arisen
amongst us!”
and, “God has visited his people!”
This report went out concerning him in the
whole of Judea and in all the surrounding
region.
The disciples of John told him about all
these things.
John, calling to himself two of his
disciples, sent them to Jesus, saying, “Are
you the one who is coming, or should we
look for another?”
When the men had come to him, they said,
“John the Baptiser has sent us to you, saying,
‘Are you he who comes, or should we look
for another?’” In that hour he cured many of
diseases and plagues and evil spirits; and
to many who were blind he gave sight.
Jesus answered them, “Go and tell John the
things which you have seen and heard: that
the blind receive their sight, the lame
walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear,
the dead are raised up, and the poor have
good news preached to them.
Blessed is he who finds no occasion for
stumbling in me.”
When John’s messengers had departed, he began
to tell the multitudes about John, “What
did you go out into the wilderness to see?
A reed shaken by the wind?
But what did you go out to see?
A man clothed in soft clothing?
Behold, those who are gorgeously dressed
and live delicately are in kings’ courts.
But what did you go out to see?
A prophet?
Yes, I tell you, and much more than a
prophet.
This is he of whom it is written, ‘Behold,
I send my messenger before your face, who
will prepare your way before you.’
“For I tell you, amongst those who are born
of women there is not a greater prophet than
John the Baptiser; yet he who is least in
God’s Kingdom is greater than he.”
When all the people and the tax collectors
heard this, they declared God to be just,
having been baptised with John’s baptism.
But the Pharisees and the lawyers rejected
the counsel of God, not being baptised by
him themselves.
“To what then should I compare the people
of this generation?
What are they like?
They are like children who sit in the
marketplace and call to one another, saying, ‘We
piped to you, and you didn’t dance.
We mourned, and you didn’t weep.’
For John the Baptiser came neither eating bread
nor drinking wine, and you say, ‘He has
a demon.’
The Son of Man has come eating and drinking,
and you say, ‘Behold, a glutton and a drunkard,
a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’
Wisdom is justified by all her children.”
One of the Pharisees invited him to eat
with him.
He entered into the Pharisee’s house and
sat at the table.
Behold, a woman in the city who was a
sinner, when she knew that he was reclining in
the Pharisee’s house, brought an alabaster
jar of ointment.
Standing behind at his feet weeping, she began
to wet his feet with her tears, and she
wiped them with the hair of her head,
kissed his feet, and anointed them with the ointment.
Now when the Pharisee who had invited him
saw it, he said to himself, “This man, if
he were a prophet, would have perceived who
and what kind of woman this is who touches
him, that she is a sinner.”
Jesus answered him, “Simon, I have
something to tell you.”
He said, “Teacher, say on.”
“A certain lender had two debtors.
The one owed five hundred denarii, and the
other fifty.
When they couldn’t pay, he forgave them
both.
Which of them therefore will love him
most?”
Simon answered, “He, I suppose, to whom he
forgave the most.”
He said to him, “You have judged
correctly.”
Turning to the woman, he said to Simon,
“Do you see this woman?
I entered into your house, and you gave me no
water for my feet, but she has wet my feet
with her tears, and wiped them with the
hair of her head.
You gave me no kiss, but she, since the time
I came in, has not ceased to kiss my feet.
You didn’t anoint my head with oil, but
she has anointed my feet with ointment.
Therefore I tell you, her sins, which are
many, are forgiven, for she loved much.
But one to whom little is forgiven, loves
little.”
He said to her, “Your sins are forgiven.”
Those who sat at the table with him began
to say to themselves, “Who is this who even
forgives sins?”
He said to the woman, “Your faith has
saved you.
Go in peace.”
Luke, chapter eight.
Soon afterwards, he went about through
cities and villages, preaching and bringing the
good news of God’s Kingdom.
With him were the twelve, and certain women
who had been healed of evil spirits and infirmities:
Mary who was called Magdalene, from whom
seven demons had gone out; and Joanna, the
wife of Chuzas, Herod’s steward; Susanna;
and many others who served them from their
possessions.
When a great multitude came together and people
from every city were coming to him, he
spoke by a parable: “The farmer went out
to sow his seed.
As he sowed, some fell along the road, and
it was trampled under foot, and the birds
of the sky devoured it.
Other seed fell on the rock, and as soon
as it grew, it withered away, because it had
no moisture.
Other fell amid the thorns, and the thorns
grew with it and choked it.
Other fell into the good ground and grew
and produced one hundred times as much fruit.”
As he said these things, he called out,
“He who has ears to hear, let him
hear!”
Then his disciples asked him, “What does
this parable mean?”
He said, “To you it is given to know
the mysteries of God’s Kingdom, but to the rest
it is given in parables, that ‘seeing they
may not see, and hearing they may not understand.’
“Now the parable is this: The seed is the
word of God.
Those along the road are those who hear;
then the devil comes and takes away the word
from their heart, that they may not
believe and be saved.
Those on the rock are they who, when they
hear, receive the word with joy; but these
have no root.
They believe for a while, then fall away
in time of temptation.
What fell amongst the thorns, these are those
who have heard, and as they go on their
way they are choked with cares, riches, and
pleasures of life; and they bring no fruit
to maturity.
Those in the good ground, these are those
who with an honest and good heart, having heard
the word, hold it tightly, and produce
fruit with perseverance.
“No one, when he has lit a lamp, covers it
with a container or puts it under a bed; but
puts it on a stand, that those who enter
in may see the light.
For nothing is hidden that will not be
revealed, nor anything secret that will not be
known and come to light.
Be careful therefore how you hear.
For whoever has, to him will be given;
and whoever doesn’t have, from him will be taken
away even that which he thinks he has.”
His mother and brothers came to him, and
they could not come near him for the crowd.
Some people told him, “Your mother and
your brothers stand outside, desiring to see you.”
But he answered them, “My mother and my brothers
are these who hear the word of God and
do it.”
Now on one of those days, he entered into
a boat, himself and his disciples, and
he said to them, “Let’s go over to the
other side of the lake.”
So they launched out.
But as they sailed, he fell asleep.
A wind storm came down on the lake,
and they were taking on dangerous amounts of water.
They came to him and awoke him, saying,
“Master, Master, we are dying!”
He awoke and rebuked the wind and the raging
of the water; then they ceased, and it was
calm.
He said to them, “Where is your faith?”
Being afraid, they marvelled, saying to one
another, “Who is this then, that he commands
even the winds and the water, and they
obey him?”
Then they arrived at the country of the
Gadarenes, which is opposite Galilee.
When Jesus stepped ashore, a certain man out of
the city who had demons for a long time
met him.
He wore no clothes, and didn’t live in a
house, but in the tombs.
When he saw Jesus, he cried out and fell
down before him, and with a loud voice said,
“What do I have to do with you, Jesus, you
Son of the Most High God?
I beg you, don’t torment me!”
For Jesus was commanding the unclean
spirit to come out of the man.
For the unclean spirit had often seized
the man.
He was kept under guard and bound with
chains and fetters.
Breaking the bonds apart, he was driven by
the demon into the desert.
Jesus asked him, “What is your name?”
He said, “Legion,” for many demons had
entered into him.
They begged him that he would not command
them to go into the abyss.
Now there was there a herd of many
pigs feeding on the mountain, and they begged him
that he would allow them to enter into
those.
Then he allowed them.
The demons came out of the man and entered
into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the
steep bank into the lake and were drowned.
When those who fed them saw what had happened,
they fled and told it in the city and
in the country.
People went out to see what had happened.
They came to Jesus and found the man from
whom the demons had gone out, sitting at Jesus’
feet, clothed and in his right mind; and
they were afraid.
Those who saw it told them how he who had
been possessed by demons was healed.
All the people of the surrounding country of
the Gadarenes asked him to depart from them,
for they were very much afraid.
Then he entered into the boat and
returned.
But the man from whom the demons had gone
out begged him that he might go with him, but
Jesus sent him away, saying, “Return to
your house, and declare what great things God
has done for you.”
He went his way, proclaiming throughout the
whole city what great things Jesus had done
for him.
When Jesus returned, the multitude welcomed him,
for they were all waiting for him.
Behold, a man named Jairus came.
He was a ruler of the synagogue.
He fell down at Jesus’ feet and begged him
to come into his house, for he had an only
born daughter, about twelve years of age,
and she was dying.
But as he went, the multitudes pressed
against him.
A woman who had a flow of blood for
twelve years, who had spent all her living on physicians
and could not be healed by any, came
behind him and touched the fringe of his cloak.
Immediately the flow of her blood stopped.
Jesus said, “Who touched me?”
When all denied it, Peter and those with
him said, “Master, the multitudes press
and jostle you, and you say, ‘Who touched
me?’” But Jesus said, “Someone did
touch me, for I perceived that power has
gone out of me.”
When the woman saw that she was not
hidden, she came trembling; and falling down before
him declared to him in the presence of all
the people the reason why she had touched
him, and how she was healed immediately.
He said to her, “Daughter, cheer up.
Your faith has made you well.
Go in peace.”
While he still spoke, one from the ruler
of the synagogue’s house came, saying to him,
“Your daughter is dead.
Don’t trouble the Teacher.”
But Jesus hearing it, answered him, “Don’t
be afraid.
Only believe, and she will be healed.”
When he came to the house, he didn’t
allow anyone to enter in, except Peter, John, James,
the father of the child, and her mother.
All were weeping and mourning her, but he
said, “Don’t weep.
She isn’t dead, but sleeping.”
They were ridiculing him, knowing that she
was dead.
But he put them all outside, and taking
her by the hand, he called, saying, “Child, arise!”
Her spirit returned, and she rose up
immediately.
He commanded that something be given to
her to eat.
Her parents were amazed, but he commanded
them to tell no one what had been done.
Luke, chapter nine.
He called the twelve together and gave
them power and authority over all demons, and
to cure diseases.
He sent them out to preach God’s Kingdom
and to heal the sick.
He said to them, “Take nothing for
your journey—no staffs, nor wallet, nor bread, nor
money.
Don’t have two tunics each.
Into whatever house you enter, stay there,
and depart from there.
As many as don’t receive you, when you
depart from that city, shake off even the dust
from your feet for a testimony against
them.”
They departed and went throughout the villages,
preaching the Good News and healing everywhere.
Now Herod the tetrarch heard of all that
was done by him; and he was very perplexed,
because it was said by some that John had
risen from the dead, and by some that Elijah
had appeared, and by others that one of
the old prophets had risen again.
Herod said, “I beheaded John, but who is
this about whom I hear such things?”
He sought to see him.
The apostles, when they had returned, told
him what things they had done.
He took them and withdrew apart to a
desert region of a city called Bethsaida.
But the multitudes, perceiving it,
followed him.
He welcomed them, spoke to them of God’s
Kingdom, and he cured those who needed healing.
The day began to wear away; and the twelve
came and said to him, “Send the multitude
away, that they may go into the surrounding
villages and farms and lodge and get food,
for we are here in a deserted place.”
But he said to them, “You give them
something to eat.”
They said, “We have no more than five loaves
and two fish, unless we should go and buy
food for all these people.”
For they were about five thousand men.
He said to his disciples, “Make them sit
down in groups of about fifty each.”
They did so, and made them all sit down.
He took the five loaves and the two fish,
and looking up to the sky, he blessed them,
broke them, and gave them to the disciples
to set before the multitude.
They ate and were all filled.
They gathered up twelve baskets of broken
pieces that were left over.
As he was praying alone, the disciples were
near him, and he asked them, “Who do the
multitudes say that I am?”
They answered, “‘John the Baptiser,’ but
others say, ‘Elijah,’ and others,
that one of the old prophets has risen
again.”
He said to them, “But who do you say that
I am?”
Peter answered, “The Christ of God.”
But he warned them and commanded them to tell
this to no one, saying, “The Son of Man
must suffer many things, and be rejected
by the elders, chief priests, and scribes,
and be killed, and the third day be raised
up.”
He said to all, “If anyone desires to come
after me, let him deny himself, take
up his cross, and follow me.
For whoever desires to save his life will
lose it, but whoever will lose his life for
my sake will save it.
For what does it profit a man if he gains
the whole world, and loses or forfeits his
own self?
For whoever will be ashamed of me and of my
words, of him will the Son of Man be ashamed
when he comes in his glory, and the glory
of the Father, and of the holy angels.
But I tell you the truth: There are some of
those who stand here who will in no way taste
of death until they see God’s Kingdom.”
About eight days after these sayings, he
took with him Peter, John, and James, and
went up onto the mountain to pray.
As he was praying, the appearance of his
face was altered, and his clothing became white
and dazzling.
Behold, two men were talking with him, who
were Moses and Elijah, who appeared in glory
and spoke of his departure, which he was
about to accomplish at Jerusalem.
Now Peter and those who were with him were
heavy with sleep, but when they were fully
awake, they saw his glory, and the two men
who stood with him.
As they were parting from him, Peter said
to Jesus, “Master, it is good for us to
be here.
Let’s make three tents: one for you, one
for Moses, and one for Elijah,” not
knowing what he said.
While he said these things, a cloud
came and overshadowed them, and they were afraid
as they entered into the cloud.
A voice came out of the cloud, saying,
“This is my beloved Son.
Listen to him!”
When the voice came, Jesus was found
alone.
They were silent, and told no one in those
days any of the things which they had seen.
On the next day, when they had come
down from the mountain, a great multitude met him.
Behold, a man from the crowd called out,
saying, “Teacher, I beg you to
look at my son, for he is my only born
child.
Behold, a spirit takes him, he suddenly cries
out, and it convulses him so that he foams;
and it hardly departs from him, bruising
him severely.
I begged your disciples to cast it out,
and they couldn’t.”
Jesus answered, “Faithless and perverse generation, how
long shall I be with you and
bear with you?
Bring your son here.”
While he was still coming, the demon threw
him down and convulsed him violently.
But Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, healed the
boy, and gave him back to his father.
They were all astonished at the majesty of
God.
But while all were marvelling at all the
things which Jesus did, he said to his disciples,
“Let these words sink into your ears, for the
Son of Man will be delivered up into the
hands of men.”
But they didn’t understand this saying.
It was concealed from them, that they should
not perceive it, and they were afraid to
ask him about this saying.
An argument arose amongst them about which
of them was the greatest.
Jesus, perceiving the reasoning of their hearts,
took a little child, and set him by
his side, and said to them, “Whoever receives
this little child in my name receives me.
Whoever receives me receives him who sent
me.
For whoever is least amongst you all, this
one will be great.”
John answered, “Master, we saw someone casting
out demons in your name, and we forbade
him, because he doesn’t follow with us.”
Jesus said to him, “Don’t forbid him, for
he who is not against us is for us.”
It came to pass, when the days were near
that he should be taken up, he intently set
his face to go to Jerusalem and sent
messengers before his face.
They went and entered into a village of
the Samaritans, so as to prepare for him.
They didn’t receive him, because he was
travelling with his face set towards Jerusalem.
When his disciples, James and John, saw
this, they said, “Lord, do you
want us to command fire to come down from
the sky and destroy them, just as Elijah did?”
But he turned and rebuked them, “You don’t
know of what kind of spirit you are.
For the Son of Man didn’t come to destroy
men’s lives, but to save them.”
They went to another village.
As they went on the way, a certain man
said to him, “I want to follow you wherever you
go, Lord.”
Jesus said to him, “The foxes have holes
and the birds of the sky have nests, but
the Son of Man has no place to lay his
head.”
He said to another, “Follow me!”
But he said, “Lord, allow me first to go
and bury my father.”
But Jesus said to him, “Leave the dead to
bury their own dead, but you go and
announce God’s Kingdom.”
Another also said, “I want to follow you,
Lord, but first allow me to say good-bye to
those who are at my house.”
But Jesus said to him, “No one, having put
his hand to the plough and looking back, is
fit for God’s Kingdom.”
Luke, chapter ten.
Now after these things, the Lord also
appointed seventy others, and sent them two by
two ahead of him into every city and place
where he was about to come.
Then he said to them, “The harvest
is indeed plentiful, but the labourers are few.
Pray therefore to the Lord of the harvest,
that he may send out labourers into his harvest.
Go your ways.
Behold, I send you out as lambs amongst
wolves.
Carry no purse, nor wallet, nor sandals.
Greet no one on the way.
Into whatever house you enter, first say,
‘Peace be to this house.’
If a son of peace is there, your peace will
rest on him; but if not, it will return to
you.
Remain in that same house, eating and
drinking the things they give, for the labourer
is worthy of his wages.
Don’t go from house to house.
Into whatever city you enter and they receive
you, eat the things that are set before
you.
Heal the sick who are there and tell them,
‘God’s Kingdom has come near to you.’
But into whatever city you enter and they
don’t receive you, go out into its streets
and say, ‘Even the dust from your city
that clings to us, we wipe off against you.
Nevertheless know this, that God’s Kingdom
has come near to you.’
I tell you, it will be more tolerable in
that day for Sodom than for that city.
“Woe to you, Chorazin!
Woe to you, Bethsaida!
For if the mighty works had been done in
Tyre and Sidon which were done in you, they
would have repented long ago, sitting in
sackcloth and ashes.
But it will be more tolerable for Tyre and
Sidon in the judgement than for you.
You, Capernaum, who are exalted to heaven,
will be brought down to Hades.
Whoever listens to you listens to me, and
whoever rejects you rejects me.
Whoever rejects me
rejects him who sent me.”
The seventy returned with joy, saying, “Lord, even
the demons are subject to us in your
name!”
He said to them, “I saw Satan having
fallen like lightning from heaven.
Behold, I give you authority to tread on
serpents and scorpions, and over all the power
of the enemy.
Nothing will in any way hurt you.
Nevertheless, don’t rejoice in this, that
the spirits are subject to you, but
rejoice that your names are written in
heaven.”
In that same hour, Jesus rejoiced in the
Holy Spirit, and said, “I thank you,
O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that
you have hidden these things from the wise and
understanding, and revealed them to little
children.
Yes, Father, for so it was well-pleasing
in your sight.”
Turning to the disciples, he said, “All things
have been delivered to me by my Father.
No one knows who the Son is, except the
Father, and who the Father is, except the
Son, and he to whomever the Son desires to
reveal him.”
Turning to the disciples, he said privately,
“Blessed are the eyes which see the things
that you see, for I tell you that many
prophets and kings desired to see the things which
you see, and didn’t see them, and to hear
the things which you hear, and didn’t hear
them.”
Behold, a certain lawyer stood up and
tested him, saying, “Teacher, what shall
I do to inherit eternal life?”
He said to him, “What is written in the
law?
How do you read it?”
He answered, “You shall love the Lord your
God with all your heart, with all your soul,
with all your strength, and with all your
mind; and your neighbour as yourself.”
He said to him, “You have answered
correctly.
Do this, and you will live.”
But he, desiring to justify himself, asked
Jesus, “Who is my neighbour?”
Jesus answered, “A certain man was going
down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and he fell
amongst robbers, who both stripped him and
beat him, and departed, leaving him half dead.
By chance a certain priest was going down
that way.
When he saw him, he passed by on the other
side.
In the same way a Levite also, when he came
to the place and saw him, passed by on the
other side.
But a certain Samaritan, as he travelled,
came where he was.
When he saw him, he was moved with
compassion, came to him, and bound up his wounds,
pouring on oil and wine.
He set him on his own animal, brought him
to an inn, and took care of him.
On the next day, when he departed, he took
out two denarii, gave them to the host, and
said to him, ‘Take care of him.
Whatever you spend beyond that, I will
repay you when I return.’
Now which of these three do you think seemed
to be a neighbour to him who fell amongst
the robbers?”
He said, “He who showed mercy on him.”
Then Jesus said to him, “Go and do
likewise.”
As they went on their way, he entered into
a certain village, and a certain woman
named Martha received him into her house.
She had a sister called Mary, who also sat
at Jesus’ feet and heard his word.
But Martha was distracted with much serving, and
she came up to him, and said, “Lord,
don’t you care that my sister left me to
serve alone?
Ask her therefore to help me.”
Jesus answered her, “Martha, Martha, you
are anxious and troubled about many things,
but one thing is needed.
Mary has chosen the good part, which will
not be taken away from her.”
Luke, chapter eleven.
When he finished praying in a certain place,
one of his disciples said to him, “Lord,
teach us to pray, just as John also taught
his disciples.”
He said to them, “When you pray, say, ‘Our
Father in heaven, may your name be kept holy.
May your Kingdom come.
May your will be done on earth, as it is
in heaven.
Give us day by day our daily bread.
Forgive us our sins, for we ourselves also
forgive everyone who is indebted to us.
Bring us not into temptation, but deliver us
from the evil one.’” He said to them, “Which
of you, if you go to a friend at midnight
and tell him, ‘Friend, lend me three
loaves of bread, for a friend of mine has
come to me from a journey, and I have nothing
to set before him,’ and he from within
will answer and say, ‘Don’t bother me.
The door is now shut, and my children are
with me in bed.
I can’t get up and give it to you’?
I tell you, although he will not rise and
give it to him because he is his friend, yet
because of his persistence, he will get up
and give him as many as he needs.
“I tell you, keep asking, and it will be
given you.
Keep seeking, and you
will find.
Keep knocking, and it will be opened to
you.
For everyone who asks receives.
He who seeks finds.
To him who knocks it will be opened.
“Which of you fathers, if your son asks
for bread, will give him a stone?
Or if he asks for a fish, he won’t give
him a snake instead of a fish, will he?
Or if he asks for an egg, he won’t give
him a scorpion, will he?
If you then, being evil, know how to give
good gifts to your children, how much
more will your heavenly Father give the
Holy Spirit to those who ask him?”
He was casting out a demon, and it was
mute.
When the demon had gone out, the mute man
spoke; and the multitudes marvelled.
But some of them said, “He casts out
demons by Beelzebul, the prince of the demons.”
Others, testing him, sought from him a
sign from heaven.
But he, knowing their thoughts, said to
them, “Every kingdom divided against itself is
brought to desolation.
A house divided against itself falls.
If Satan also is divided against himself,
how will his kingdom stand?
For you say that I cast out demons by
Beelzebul.
But if I cast out demons by Beelzebul, by
whom do your children cast them out?
Therefore they will be your judges.
But if I by God’s finger cast out demons,
then God’s Kingdom has come to you.
“When the strong man, fully armed, guards
his own dwelling, his goods are safe.
But when someone stronger attacks him and
overcomes him, he takes from him his whole
armour in which he trusted, and divides
his plunder.
“He who is not with me is against me.
He who doesn’t gather with me scatters.
The unclean spirit, when he has gone out
of the man, passes through dry places, seeking
rest; and finding none, he says, ‘I will turn
back to my house from which I came out.’
When he returns, he finds it swept and put
in order.
Then he goes and takes seven other spirits
more evil than himself, and they enter in
and dwell there.
The last state of that man becomes worse
than the first.”
It came to pass, as he said these
things, a certain woman out of the multitude lifted
up her voice and said to him, “Blessed is
the womb that bore you, and the breasts which
nursed you!”
But he said, “On the contrary, blessed are
those who hear the word of God, and keep
it.”
When the multitudes were gathering together to him,
he began to say, “This is an evil
generation.
It seeks after a sign.
No sign will be given to it but the sign
of Jonah the prophet.
For even as Jonah became a sign to the
Ninevites, so the Son of Man will also be to
this generation.
The Queen of the South will rise up in the
judgement with the men of this generation
and will condemn them, for she came from the
ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of
Solomon; and behold, one greater than
Solomon is here.
The men of Nineveh will stand up in
the judgement with this generation, and will condemn
it, for they repented at the preaching of
Jonah; and behold, one greater than Jonah is
here.
“No one, when he has lit a lamp, puts it
in a cellar or under a basket, but on a
stand, that those who come in may see the
light.
The lamp of the body is the eye.
Therefore when your eye is good, your whole body
is also full of light; but when it is
evil, your body also is full of darkness.
Therefore see whether the light that is in
you isn’t darkness.
If therefore your whole body is full of
light, having no part dark, it will be wholly
full of light, as when the lamp with its
bright shining gives you light.”
Now as he spoke, a certain Pharisee
asked him to dine with him.
He went in and sat at the table.
When the Pharisee saw it, he marvelled that
he had not first washed himself before dinner.
The Lord said to him, “Now you Pharisees cleanse
the outside of the cup and of the platter,
but your inward part is full of extortion
and wickedness.
You foolish ones, didn’t he who made the
outside make the inside also?
But give for gifts to the needy those
things which are within, and behold, all things
will be clean to you.
But woe to you Pharisees!
For you tithe mint and rue and every herb,
but you bypass justice and God’s love.
You ought to have done these, and not to
have left the other undone.
Woe to you Pharisees!
For you love the best seats in
the synagogues and the greetings in the marketplaces.
Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees,
hypocrites!
For you are like hidden graves, and the
men who walk over them don’t know it.”
One of the lawyers answered him, “Teacher,
in saying this you insult us also.”
He said, “Woe to you lawyers also!
For you load men with burdens that are
difficult to carry, and you yourselves won’t even
lift one finger to help carry those
burdens.
Woe to you!
For you build the tombs of the prophets,
and your fathers killed them.
So you testify and consent to the works of
your fathers.
For they killed them, and you build their
tombs.
Therefore also the wisdom of God said, ‘I
will send to them prophets and apostles; and
some of them they will kill and persecute,
that the blood of all the prophets, which
was shed from the foundation of the world,
may be required of this generation, from the
blood of Abel to the blood of Zachariah,
who perished between the altar and the sanctuary.’
Yes, I tell you, it will be required of
this generation.
Woe to you lawyers!
For you took away the key of knowledge.
You didn’t enter in yourselves, and those
who were entering in, you hindered.”
As he said these things to them, the
scribes and the Pharisees began to be terribly angry,
and to draw many things out of him, lying
in wait for him, and seeking to catch him in
something he might say, that they might
accuse him.
Luke, chapter twelve.
Meanwhile, when a multitude of many thousands
had gathered together, so much so that
they trampled on each other, he began to
tell his disciples first of all, “Beware of
the yeast of the Pharisees, which is
hypocrisy.
But there is nothing covered up that will
not be revealed, nor hidden that will not be
known.
Therefore whatever you have said in the
darkness will be heard in the light.
What you have spoken in the ear in
the inner rooms will be proclaimed on the housetops.
“I tell you, my friends, don’t be afraid of
those who kill the body, and after that have
no more that they can do.
But I will warn you whom you should fear.
Fear him who after he has killed, has
power to cast into Gehenna.
Yes, I tell you, fear him.
“Aren’t five sparrows sold for two assaria
coins?
Not one of them is forgotten by God.
But the very hairs of your head are
all counted.
Therefore don’t be afraid.
You are of more value than many sparrows.
“I tell you, everyone who confesses me before
men, the Son of Man will also confess before
the angels of God; but he who denies me in
the presence of men will be denied in the
presence of God’s angels.
Everyone who speaks a word against the Son
of Man will be forgiven, but those who blaspheme
against the Holy Spirit will not be
forgiven.
When they bring you before the synagogues,
the rulers, and the authorities, don’t be
anxious how or what you will answer or what
you will say; for the Holy Spirit will teach
you in that same hour what you must say.”
One of the multitude said to him,
“Teacher, tell my brother to divide the inheritance
with me.”
But he said to him, “Man, who made me a
judge or an arbitrator over you?”
He said to them, “Beware!
Keep yourselves from covetousness, for a
man’s life doesn’t consist of the abundance
of the things which he possesses.”
He spoke a parable to them, saying, “The
ground of a certain rich man produced abundantly.
He reasoned within himself, saying, ‘What will I
do, because I don’t have room to store
my crops?’
He said, ‘This is what I will do.
I will pull down my barns, build bigger ones,
and there I will store all my grain and
my goods.
I will tell my soul, “Soul, you have many
goods laid up for many years.
Take your ease, eat, drink, and be merry.”’
“But God said to him, ‘You foolish one, tonight
your soul is required of you.
The things which you have prepared—whose
will they be?’
So is he who lays up treasure for himself,
and is not rich towards God.”
He said to his disciples, “Therefore I tell
you, don’t be anxious for your life, what
you will eat, nor yet for your body, what
you will wear.
Life is more than food, and the body is
more than clothing.
Consider the ravens: they don’t sow, they
don’t reap, they have no warehouse or barn,
and God feeds them.
How much more valuable are you than birds!
Which of you by being anxious can add a
cubit to his height?
If then you aren’t able to do even the
least things, why are you anxious about the rest?
Consider the lilies, how they grow.
They don’t toil, neither do they spin; yet
I tell you, even Solomon in all his glory
was not arrayed like one of these.
But if this is how God clothes the
grass in the field, which today exists and tomorrow
is cast into the oven, how much more will
he clothe you, O you of little faith?
“Don’t seek what you will eat or what you
will drink; neither be anxious.
For the nations of the world seek after
all of these things, but your Father knows that
you need these things.
But seek God’s Kingdom, and all these
things will be added to you.
“Don’t be afraid, little flock, for it is
your Father’s good pleasure to give you the
Kingdom.
Sell what you have and give gifts to the
needy.
Make for yourselves purses which don’t grow
old, a treasure in the heavens that doesn’t
fail, where no thief approaches and no
moth destroys.
For where your treasure is, there will
your heart be also.
“Let your waist be dressed and your lamps
burning.
Be like men watching for their lord when
he returns from the wedding feast, that when
he comes and knocks, they may immediately
open to him.
Blessed are those servants whom the lord
will find watching when he comes.
Most certainly I tell you that he will
dress himself, make them recline, and will come
and serve them.
They will be blessed if he comes in the
second or third watch and finds them so.
But know this, that if the master of the
house had known in what hour the thief was coming,
he would have watched and not allowed his
house to be broken into.
Therefore be ready also, for the Son of Man
is coming in an hour that you don’t expect
him.”
Peter said to him, “Lord, are you telling
this parable to us, or to everybody?”
The Lord said, “Who then is the faithful
and wise steward, whom his lord will set over
his household, to give them their portion
of food at the right times?
Blessed is that servant whom his lord will
find doing so when he comes.
Truly I tell you that he will set him over
all that he has.
But if that servant says in his heart,
‘My lord delays his coming,’ and begins to beat
the menservants and the maidservants, and to eat
and drink and to be drunken, then the
lord of that servant will come in a day
when he isn’t expecting him and in an hour that
he doesn’t know, and will cut him in two,
and place his portion with the unfaithful.
That servant who knew his lord’s will, and
didn’t prepare nor do what he wanted, will
be beaten with many stripes, but he who
didn’t know, and did things worthy of stripes,
will be beaten with few stripes.
To whomever much is given, of him will
much be required; and to whom much was entrusted,
of him more will be asked.
“I came to throw fire on the earth.
I wish it were already kindled.
But I have a baptism to be baptised with,
and how distressed I am until it is accomplished!
Do you think that I have come to give
peace in the earth?
I tell you, no, but rather division.
For from now on, there will be five in one
house divided, three against two, and
two against three.
They will be divided, father against son,
and son against father; mother against
daughter, and daughter against her mother;
mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law,
and daughter-in-law against her
mother-in-law.”
He said to the multitudes also, “When you
see a cloud rising from the west, immediately
you say, ‘A shower is coming,’ and so it
happens.
When a south wind blows, you say, ‘There
will be a scorching heat,’ and it
happens.
You hypocrites!
You know how to interpret the appearance of the
earth and the sky, but how is it that
you don’t interpret this time?
“Why don’t you judge for yourselves what
is right?
For when you are going with your
adversary before the magistrate, try diligently on the
way to be released from him, lest perhaps he
drag you to the judge, and the judge deliver
you to the officer, and the officer throw
you into prison.
I tell you, you will by no means get out
of there until you have paid the very last penny.”
Luke, chapter thirteen.
Now there were some present at the same
time who told him about the Galileans whose blood
Pilate had mixed with their sacrifices.
Jesus answered them, “Do you think that
these Galileans were worse sinners than all the
other Galileans, because they suffered
such things?
I tell you, no, but unless you repent, you
will all perish in the same way.
Or those eighteen on whom the tower in
Siloam fell and killed them—do you think that
they were worse offenders than all the men
who dwell in Jerusalem?
I tell you, no, but, unless you repent,
you will all perish in the same way.”
He spoke this parable.
“A certain man had a fig tree planted in
his vineyard, and he came seeking fruit on it
and found none.
He said to the vine dresser, ‘Behold, these
three years I have come looking for fruit
on this fig tree, and found none.
Cut it down!
Why does it waste the soil?’
He answered, ‘Lord, leave it alone this
year also, until I dig around it and
fertilise it.
If it bears fruit, fine; but if not, after
that, you can cut it down.’” He
was teaching in one of the synagogues on
the Sabbath day.
Behold, there was a woman who had a spirit
of infirmity eighteen years.
She was bent over and could in no way
straighten herself up.
When Jesus saw her, he called her and said
to her, “Woman, you are freed from your infirmity.”
He laid his hands on her, and immediately
she stood up straight and glorified God.
The ruler of the synagogue, being indignant
because Jesus had healed on the Sabbath,
said to the multitude, “There are six days
in which men ought to work.
Therefore come on those days and be
healed, and not on the Sabbath day!”
Therefore the Lord answered him, “You
hypocrites!
Doesn’t each one of you free his ox or
his donkey from the stall on the Sabbath and lead
him away to water?
Ought not this woman, being a daughter of
Abraham whom Satan had bound eighteen long
years, be freed from this bondage on the
Sabbath day?”
As he said these things, all his
adversaries were disappointed; and all the multitude
rejoiced for all the glorious things that
were done by him.
He said, “What is God’s Kingdom like?
To what shall I compare it?
It is like a grain of mustard seed which a
man took and put in his own garden.
It grew and became a large tree, and the
birds of the sky live in its branches.”
Again he said, “To what shall I compare
God’s Kingdom?
It is like yeast, which a woman took and
hid in three measures of flour, until it was
all leavened.”
He went on his way through cities
and villages, teaching, and travelling on to Jerusalem.
One said to him, “Lord, are they few who
are saved?”
He said to them, “Strive to enter in by
the narrow door, for many, I tell you,
will seek to enter in and will not be
able.
When once the master of the house has risen
up and has shut the door, and you begin to
stand outside and to knock at the door,
saying, ‘Lord, Lord, open to
us!’
then he will answer and tell you, ‘I don’t
know you or where you come from.’
Then you will begin to say, ‘We ate and
drank in your presence, and you taught in our
streets.’
He will say, ‘I tell you, I don’t know
where you come from.
Depart from me, all you workers of
iniquity.’
There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth
when you see Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and all
the prophets in God’s Kingdom, and
yourselves being thrown outside.
They will come from the east, west, north,
and south, and will sit down in God’s Kingdom.
Behold, there are some who are last who will
be first, and there are some who are first
who will be last.”
On that same day, some Pharisees came,
saying to him, “Get out of here and go
away, for Herod wants to kill you.”
He said to them, “Go and tell that fox,
‘Behold, I cast out demons and perform
cures today and tomorrow, and the third
day I complete my mission.
Nevertheless I must go on my way today and
tomorrow and the next day, for it can’t be
that a prophet would perish outside of
Jerusalem.’
“Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kills the
prophets and stones those who are sent
to her!
How often I wanted to gather your children
together, like a hen gathers her own brood
under her wings, and you refused!
Behold, your house is left to you
desolate.
I tell you, you will not see me until you
say, ‘Blessed is he who comes in the name of
the Lord!’” Luke, chapter fourteen.
When he went into the house of one of
the rulers of the Pharisees on a Sabbath to eat
bread, they were watching him.
Behold, a certain man who had dropsy was
in front of him.
Jesus, answering, spoke to the lawyers and
Pharisees, saying, “Is it lawful to
heal on the Sabbath?”
But they were silent.
He took him, and healed him, and let him
go.
He answered them, “Which of you, if your
son or an ox fell into a well, wouldn’t
immediately pull him out on a Sabbath
day?”
They couldn’t answer him regarding these
things.
He spoke a parable to those who were
invited, when he noticed how they chose the best
seats, and said to them, “When you are
invited by anyone to a wedding feast, don’t
sit in the best seat, since perhaps
someone more honourable than you might be invited
by him, and he who invited both of you
would come and tell you, ‘Make room
for this person.’
Then you would begin, with shame, to take
the lowest place.
But when you are invited, go and sit in
the lowest place, so that when he who invited
you comes, he may tell you, ‘Friend, move
up higher.’
Then you will be honoured in the presence
of all who sit at the table with you.
For everyone who exalts himself will be
humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be
exalted.”
He also said to the one who had invited
him, “When you make a dinner or a supper, don’t
call your friends, nor your brothers, nor
your kinsmen, nor rich neighbours, or perhaps
they might also return the favour, and pay
you back.
But when you make a feast, ask the poor,
the maimed, the lame, or the blind; and
you will be blessed, because they don’t
have the resources to repay you.
For you will be repaid in the resurrection
of the righteous.”
When one of those who sat at the table
with him heard these things, he said to him, “Blessed
is he who will feast in God’s Kingdom!”
But he said to him, “A certain man made a
great supper, and he invited many people.
He sent out his servant at supper time
to tell those who were invited, ‘Come, for everything
is ready now.’
They all as one began to make excuses.
“The first said to him, ‘I have bought a
field, and I must go and see it.
Please have me excused.’
“Another said, ‘I have bought five yoke of
oxen, and I must go try them out.
Please have me excused.’
“Another said, ‘I have married a wife, and
therefore I can’t come.’
“That servant came, and told his lord
these things.
Then the master of the house, being angry,
said to his servant, ‘Go out quickly into
the streets and lanes of the city, and
bring in the poor, maimed, blind, and lame.’
“The servant said, ‘Lord, it is done as
you commanded, and there is still room.’
“The lord said to the servant, ‘Go out
into the highways and hedges, and compel them
to come in, that my house may be filled.
For I tell you that none of those men
who were invited will taste of my supper.’” Now
great multitudes were going with him.
He turned and said to them, “If anyone
comes to me, and doesn’t disregard his own father,
mother, wife, children, brothers, and
sisters, yes, and his own life also, he
can’t be my disciple.
Whoever doesn’t bear his own cross and
come after me, can’t be my disciple.
For which of you, desiring to build a
tower, doesn’t first sit down and count the cost,
to see if he has enough to complete it?
Or perhaps, when he has laid a foundation
and isn’t able to finish, everyone who
sees begins to mock him, saying, ‘This man
began to build and wasn’t able to finish.’
Or what king, as he goes to encounter another
king in war, will not sit down first and
consider whether he is able with ten thousand
to meet him who comes against him with
twenty thousand?
Or else, while the other is yet a great
way off, he sends an envoy and asks for conditions
of peace.
So therefore, whoever of you who doesn’t renounce
all that he has, he can’t be my disciple.
“Salt is good, but if the salt becomes
flat and tasteless, with what do you season it?
It is fit neither for the soil nor for the
manure pile.
It is thrown out.
He who has ears to hear, let him hear.”
Luke, chapter fifteen.
Now all the tax collectors and sinners
were coming close to him to hear him.
The Pharisees and the scribes murmured,
saying, “This man welcomes sinners, and eats
with them.”
He told them this parable: “Which of you men,
if you had one hundred sheep and lost one
of them, wouldn’t leave the ninety-nine in the
wilderness and go after the one that was
lost, until he found it?
When he has found it, he carries it on his
shoulders, rejoicing.
When he comes home, he calls together
his friends and his neighbours, saying to them,
‘Rejoice with me, for I have found my
sheep which was lost!’
I tell you that even so there will be more
joy in heaven over one sinner who repents,
than over ninety-nine righteous people who
need no repentance.
“Or what woman, if she had ten drachma
coins, if she lost one drachma coin, wouldn’t
light a lamp, sweep the house, and seek
diligently until she found it?
When she has found it, she calls
together her friends and neighbours, saying, ‘Rejoice
with me, for I have found the drachma
which I had lost!’
Even so, I tell you, there is joy in the
presence of the angels of God over
one sinner repenting.”
He said, “A certain man had two sons.
The younger of them said to his father,
‘Father, give me my share of your property.’
So he divided his livelihood between them.
Not many days after, the younger son
gathered all of this together and travelled into
a far country.
There he wasted his property with riotous
living.
When he had spent all of it, there arose
a severe famine in that country, and he began
to be in need.
He went and joined himself to one of the
citizens of that country, and he sent him into
his fields to feed pigs.
He wanted to fill his belly with the pods
that the pigs ate, but no one gave him any.
But when he came to himself, he said,
‘How many hired servants of my father’s have bread
enough to spare, and I’m dying with
hunger!
I will get up and go to my father,
and will tell him, “Father, I have sinned against
heaven and in your sight.
I am no more worthy to be called your son.
Make me as one of your hired servants.”’
“He arose and came to his father.
But while he was still far off, his father
saw him and was moved with compassion, and
ran, fell on his neck, and kissed him.
The son said to him, ‘Father, I have
sinned against heaven and in your sight.
I am no longer worthy to be called your
son.’
“But the father said to his servants, ‘Bring
out the best robe and put it on him.
Put a ring on his hand and sandals on his
feet.
Bring the fattened calf, kill it, and let’s
eat and celebrate; for this, my son, was
dead and is alive again.
He was lost and is found.’
Then they began to celebrate.
“Now his elder son was in the field.
As he came near to the house, he heard
music and dancing.
He called one of the servants to him and
asked what was going on.
He said to him, ‘Your brother has come,
and your father has killed the fattened calf,
because he has received him back safe and
healthy.’
But he was angry and would not go in.
Therefore his father came out and begged
him.
But he answered his father, ‘Behold, these
many years I have served you, and I never
disobeyed a commandment of yours, but you never
gave me a goat, that I might celebrate
with my friends.
But when this your son came, who
has devoured your living with prostitutes, you killed
the fattened calf for him.’
“He said to him, ‘Son, you are always with
me, and all that is mine is yours.
But it was appropriate to celebrate and be
glad, for this, your brother, was dead, and
is alive again.
He was lost, and is found.’” Luke, chapter
sixteen.
He also said to his disciples, “There was
a certain rich man who had a manager.
An accusation was made to him that this
man was wasting his possessions.
He called him, and said to him, ‘What is
this that I hear about you?
Give an accounting of your management, for
you can no longer be manager.’
“The manager said within himself, ‘What will I
do, seeing that my lord is taking away
the management position from me?
I don’t have strength to dig.
I am ashamed to beg.
I know what I will do, so that when
I am removed from management, they may receive me
into their houses.’
Calling each one of his lord’s debtors to him,
he said to the first, ‘How much do you
owe to my lord?’
He said, ‘A hundred batos of oil.’
He said to him, ‘Take your bill, and sit
down quickly and write fifty.’
Then he said to another, ‘How much do you
owe?’
He said, ‘A hundred cors of wheat.’
He said to him, ‘Take your bill, and write
eighty.’
“His lord commended the dishonest manager because
he had done wisely, for the children
of this world are, in their own
generation, wiser than the children of the light.
I tell you, make for yourselves friends by
means of unrighteous mammon, so that when
you fail, they may receive you into the
eternal tents.
He who is faithful in a very little is
faithful also in much.
He who is dishonest in a very little is
also dishonest in much.
If therefore you have not been faithful in
the unrighteous mammon, who will commit to
your trust the true riches?
If you have not been faithful in that
which is another’s, who will give you that which
is your own?
No servant can serve two masters, for either
he will hate the one and love the other;
or else he will hold to one and despise
the other.
You aren’t able to serve God and Mammon.”
The Pharisees, who were lovers of money,
also heard all these things, and they scoffed
at him.
He said to them, “You are those who justify
yourselves in the sight of men, but God knows
your hearts.
For that which is exalted amongst men is
an abomination in the sight of God.
“The law and the prophets were until John.
From that time the Good News of God’s
Kingdom is preached, and everyone is forcing his
way into it.
But it is easier for heaven and earth to
pass away than for one tiny stroke of a pen
in the law to fall.
“Everyone who divorces his wife and
marries another commits adultery.
He who marries one who is divorced from a
husband commits adultery.
“Now there was a certain rich man, and
he was clothed in purple and fine linen, living
in luxury every day.
A certain beggar, named Lazarus, was taken
to his gate, full of sores, and desiring
to be fed with the crumbs that fell from
the rich man’s table.
Yes, even the dogs came and licked his
sores.
The beggar died, and he was carried away
by the angels to Abraham’s bosom.
The rich man also died and was buried.
In Hades, he lifted up his eyes, being in
torment, and saw Abraham far off, and
Lazarus at his bosom.
He cried and said, ‘Father Abraham, have
mercy on me, and send Lazarus, that
he may dip the tip of his finger in water
and cool my tongue!
For I am in anguish in this flame.’
“But Abraham said, ‘Son, remember that you,
in your lifetime, received your good things,
and Lazarus, in the same way, bad things.
But here he is now comforted and you are
in anguish.
Besides all this, between us and you there
is a great gulf fixed, that those who want
to pass from here to you are not able, and
that no one may cross over from there to us.’
“He said, ‘I ask you therefore, father, that
you would send him to my father’s house—
for I have five brothers—that he may testify
to them, so they won’t also come into this
place of torment.’
“But Abraham said to him, ‘They have Moses
and the prophets.
Let them listen to them.’
“He said, ‘No, father Abraham, but if one
goes to them from the dead, they will
repent.’
“He said to him, ‘If they don’t listen
to Moses and the prophets, neither will they be
persuaded if one rises from the dead.’”
Luke, chapter seventeen.
He said to the disciples, “It is
impossible that no occasions of stumbling should come,
but woe to him through whom they come!
It would be better for him if a millstone
were hung around his neck, and he were thrown
into the sea, rather than that he should
cause one of these little ones to stumble.
Be careful.
If your brother sins against you, rebuke
him.
If he repents, forgive him.
If he sins against you seven times in the
day, and seven times returns, saying, ‘I
repent,’ you shall forgive him.”
The apostles said to the Lord, “Increase
our faith.”
The Lord said, “If you had faith like a
grain of mustard seed, you would tell this sycamore
tree, ‘Be uprooted and be planted in the
sea,’ and it would obey you.
But who is there amongst you, having
a servant ploughing or keeping sheep, that will
say when he comes in from the field, ‘Come
immediately and sit down at the table’?
Wouldn’t he rather tell him, ‘Prepare
my supper, clothe yourself properly, and serve
me while I eat and drink.
Afterward you shall eat and drink’?
Does he thank that servant because he did
the things that were commanded?
I think not.
Even so you also, when you have done
all the things that are commanded you, say, ‘We
are unworthy servants.
We have done our duty.’” As he was on his
way to Jerusalem, he was passing along the
borders of Samaria and Galilee.
As he entered into a certain village, ten men
who were lepers met him, who stood at a
distance.
They lifted up their voices, saying,
“Jesus, Master, have mercy on us!”
When he saw them, he said to them, “Go and
show yourselves to the priests.”
As they went, they were cleansed.
One of them, when he saw that he was
healed, turned back, glorifying God with a
loud voice.
He fell on his face at Jesus’ feet, giving
him thanks; and he was a Samaritan.
Jesus answered, “Weren’t the ten cleansed?
But where are the nine?
Were there none found who returned to give
glory to God, except this foreigner?”
Then he said to him, “Get up, and go your
way.
Your faith has healed you.”
Being asked by the Pharisees when God’s
Kingdom would come, he answered them, “God’s
Kingdom doesn’t come with observation;
neither will they say, ‘Look, here!’
or, ‘Look, there!’
for behold, God’s Kingdom is within you.”
He said to the disciples, “The days will come
when you will desire to see one of the
days of the Son of Man, and you will not
see it.
They will tell you, ‘Look, here!’
or ‘Look, there!’
Don’t go away or follow after them, for as
the lightning, when it flashes out of one
part under the sky, shines to another part
under the sky, so will the Son of Man
be in his day.
But first, he must suffer many things and
be rejected by this generation.
As it was in the days of Noah, even so it
will also be in the days of the Son of Man.
They ate, they drank, they married, and they
were given in marriage until the day that
Noah entered into the ship, and the flood
came and destroyed them all.
Likewise, even as it was in the days of
Lot: they ate, they drank, they
bought, they sold, they planted, they built; but
in the day that Lot went out from Sodom,
it rained fire and sulphur from the sky
and destroyed them all.
It will be the same way in the day that
the Son of Man is revealed.
In that day, he who will be on the housetop
and his goods in the house, let him not go
down to take them away.
Let him who is in the field likewise not
turn back.
Remember Lot’s wife!
Whoever seeks to save his life loses it,
but whoever loses his life preserves it.
I tell you, in that night there will be
two people in one bed.
One will be taken and the other will be
left.
There will be two grinding grain together.
One will be taken and the other will be
left.”
They, answering, asked him, “Where, Lord?”
He said to them, “Where the body is,
there the vultures will also be gathered together.”
Luke, chapter eighteen.
He also spoke a parable to them that they
must always pray and not give up, saying,
“There was a judge in a certain city who
didn’t fear God and didn’t respect man.
A widow was in that city, and she often
came to him, saying, ‘Defend me from my adversary!’
He wouldn’t for a while; but afterward he
said to himself, ‘Though I neither fear God
nor respect man, yet because this widow
bothers me, I will defend her, or
else she will wear me out by her
continual coming.’” The Lord said, “Listen to what the
unrighteous judge says.
Won’t God avenge his chosen ones who are crying
out to him day and night, and yet he
exercises patience with them?
I tell you that he will avenge them
quickly.
Nevertheless, when the Son of Man comes,
will he find faith on the earth?”
He also spoke this parable to certain
people who were convinced of their own righteousness,
and who despised all others: “Two men went
up into the temple to pray; one was
a Pharisee, and the other was a tax
collector.
The Pharisee stood and prayed by himself
like this: ‘God, I thank you that I
am not like the rest of
men: extortionists, unrighteous, adulterers, or even
like this tax collector.
I fast twice a week.
I give tithes of all that I get.’
But the tax collector, standing far away, wouldn’t
even lift up his eyes to heaven, but
beat his breast, saying, ‘God, be merciful
to me, a sinner!’
I tell you, this man went down to
his house justified rather than the other; for everyone
who exalts himself will be humbled, but he
who humbles himself will be exalted.”
They were also bringing their babies to
him, that he might touch them.
But when the disciples saw it, they
rebuked them.
Jesus summoned them, saying, “Allow the little
children to come to me, and don’t hinder
them, for God’s Kingdom belongs to such as
these.
Most certainly, I tell you, whoever doesn’t
receive God’s Kingdom like a little child,
he will in no way enter into it.”
A certain ruler asked him, saying, “Good
Teacher, what shall I do to inherit eternal
life?”
Jesus asked him, “Why do you call me good?
No one is good, except one: God.
You know the commandments: ‘Don’t commit
adultery,’ ‘Don’t murder,’ ‘Don’t steal,’ ‘Don’t
give false testimony,’ ‘Honour your father and
your mother.’” He said, “I have observed
all these things from my youth up.”
When Jesus heard these things, he said to
him, “You still lack one thing.
Sell all that you have and distribute it
to the poor.
Then you will have treasure in heaven;
then come, follow me.”
But when he heard these things, he became
very sad, for he was very rich.
Jesus, seeing that he became very sad,
said, “How hard it is for those who
have riches to enter into God’s Kingdom!
For it is easier for a camel to enter in
through a needle’s eye than for a rich man to
enter into God’s Kingdom.”
Those who heard it said, “Then who can be
saved?”
But he said, “The things which are
impossible with men are possible with God.”
Peter said, “Look, we have left everything
and followed you.”
He said to them, “Most certainly I tell you,
there is no one who has left house, or wife,
or brothers, or parents, or children, for
God’s Kingdom’s sake, who will not receive
many times more in this time, and in the
world to come, eternal life.”
He took the twelve aside and said to them,
“Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and
all the things that are written through the
prophets concerning the Son of Man will be
completed.
For he will be delivered up to
the Gentiles, will be mocked, treated shamefully, and
spit on.
They will scourge and kill him.
On the third day, he will rise again.”
They understood none of these things.
This saying was hidden from them, and
they didn’t understand the things that were said.
As he came near Jericho, a certain blind
man sat by the road, begging.
Hearing a multitude going by, he asked
what this meant.
They told him that Jesus of Nazareth was
passing by.
He cried out, “Jesus, you son of David,
have mercy on me!”
Those who led the way rebuked him, that he
should be quiet; but he cried out all the
more, “You son of David, have mercy on
me!”
Standing still, Jesus commanded him to be
brought to him.
When he had come near, he asked him, “What
do you want me to do?”
He said, “Lord, that I may see again.”
Jesus said to him, “Receive your sight.
Your faith has healed you.”
Immediately he received his sight and
followed him, glorifying God.
All the people, when they saw it, praised
God.
Luke, chapter nineteen.
He entered and was passing through
Jericho.
There was a man named Zacchaeus.
He was a chief tax collector, and he was
rich.
He was trying to see who Jesus was,
and couldn’t because of the crowd, because he was
short.
He ran on ahead and climbed up into a sycamore
tree to see him, for he was going to pass
that way.
When Jesus came to the place, he looked up
and saw him, and said to him, “Zacchaeus,
hurry and come down, for today I must stay
at your house.”
He hurried, came down, and received him
joyfully.
When they saw it, they all murmured, saying, “He
has gone in to lodge with a man who
is a sinner.”
Zacchaeus stood and said to the Lord, “Behold, Lord,
half of my goods I give to the poor.
If I have wrongfully exacted anything of
anyone, I restore four times as much.”
Jesus said to him, “Today, salvation has
come to this house, because he
also is a son of Abraham.
For the Son of Man came to seek and to
save that which was lost.”
As they heard these things, he went on
and told a parable, because he was near Jerusalem,
and they supposed that God’s Kingdom would
be revealed immediately.
He said therefore, “A certain nobleman
went into a far country to receive for
himself a kingdom and to return.
He called ten servants of his and gave
them ten mina coins, and told them, ‘Conduct
business until I come.’
But his citizens hated him, and sent an
envoy after him, saying, ‘We don’t want this
man to reign over us.’
“When he had come back again, having
received the kingdom, he commanded these servants,
to whom he had given the money, to be
called to him, that he might know what they had
gained by conducting business.
The first came before him, saying, ‘Lord,
your mina has made ten more minas.’
“He said to him, ‘Well done, you good
servant!
Because you were found faithful with very
little, you shall have authority over ten cities.’
“The second came, saying, ‘Your mina,
Lord, has made five minas.’
“So he said to him, ‘And you are to be
over five cities.’
Another came, saying, ‘Lord, behold, your
mina, which I kept laid away in
a handkerchief, for I feared you, because
you are an exacting man.
You take up that which you didn’t lay
down, and reap that which you didn’t sow.’
“He said to him, ‘Out of your own mouth I
will judge you, you wicked servant!
You knew that I am an exacting man, taking
up that which I didn’t lay down and reaping
that which I didn’t sow.
Then why didn’t you deposit my money in the
bank, and at my coming, I might have earned
interest on it?’
He said to those who stood by, ‘Take the mina
away from him and give it to him who has
the ten minas.’
“They said to him, ‘Lord, he has ten
minas!’
‘For I tell you that to everyone who has,
will more be given; but from him who doesn’t
have, even that which he has will be taken
away from him.
But bring those enemies of mine who didn’t
want me to reign over them here, and kill
them before me.’” Having said these things,
he went on ahead, going up to Jerusalem.
When he came near to Bethsphage and Bethany,
at the mountain that is called Olivet, he
sent two of his disciples, saying, “Go your
way into the village on the other side, in
which, as you enter, you will find a colt
tied, which no man has ever sat upon.
Untie it and bring it.
If anyone asks you, ‘Why are you untying
it?’
say to him: ‘The Lord needs it.’” Those
who were sent went away and found
things just as he had told them.
As they were untying the colt, its owners
said to them, “Why are you untying the colt?”
They said, “The Lord needs it.”
Then they brought it to Jesus.
They threw their cloaks on the colt and
sat Jesus on them.
As he went, they spread their cloaks on
the road.
As he was now getting near, at the
descent of the Mount of Olives, the whole multitude
of the disciples began to rejoice and praise
God with a loud voice for all the mighty
works which they had seen, saying, “Blessed is
the King who comes in the name of the
Lord!
Peace in heaven, and glory in the
highest!”
Some of the Pharisees from the multitude
said to him, “Teacher, rebuke your disciples!”
He answered them, “I tell you that if
these were silent, the stones would cry out.”
When he came near, he saw the city and
wept over it, saying, “If you, even
you, had known today the things which
belong to your peace!
But now, they are hidden from your eyes.
For the days will come on you when
your enemies will throw up a barricade against you,
surround you, hem you in on every side,
and will dash you and your children within you
to the ground.
They will not leave in you one stone
on another, because you didn’t know the time of
your visitation.”
He entered into the temple and began to drive
out those who bought and sold in it, saying
to them, “It is written, ‘My house is a
house of prayer,’ but
you have made it a ‘den of robbers’!”
He was teaching daily in the temple, but
the chief priests, the scribes, and the leading
men amongst the people sought to destroy
him.
They couldn’t find what they might do, for
all the people hung on to every word that
he said.
Luke, chapter twenty.
On one of those days, as he was teaching
the people in the temple and preaching the Good
News, the priests and scribes came to him
with the elders.
They asked him, “Tell us: by what
authority do you do these things?
Or who is giving you this authority?”
He answered them, “I also will ask you one
question.
Tell me: the baptism of John, was it from
heaven, or from men?”
They reasoned with themselves, saying, “If
we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why
didn’t you believe him?’
But if we say, ‘From men,’ all the people
will stone us, for they are persuaded that
John was a prophet.”
They answered that they didn’t know where
it was from.
Jesus said to them, “Neither will I tell
you by what authority I do these things.”
He began to tell the people this parable:
“A man planted a vineyard and rented it out
to some farmers, and went into another
country for a long time.
At the proper season, he sent a servant to
the farmers to collect his share of the fruit
of the vineyard.
But the farmers beat him and sent him away
empty.
He sent yet another servant, and they also
beat him and treated him shamefully, and sent
him away empty.
He sent yet a third, and they also wounded
him and threw him out.
The lord of the vineyard said, ‘What shall
I do?
I will send my beloved son.
It may be that seeing him, they will
respect him.’
“But when the farmers saw him, they
reasoned amongst themselves, saying, ‘This is the
heir.
Come, let’s kill him, that the inheritance
may be ours.’
Then they threw him out of the vineyard
and killed him.
What therefore will the lord of the
vineyard do to them?
He will come and destroy these farmers,
and will give the vineyard to others.”
When they heard that, they said, “May that
never be!”
But he looked at them and said, “Then what
is this that is written, ‘The stone which
the builders rejected was made the chief
cornerstone?’
Everyone who falls on that stone will be
broken to pieces, but it will crush whomever
it falls on to dust.”
The chief priests and the scribes sought to
lay hands on him that very hour, but they
feared the people—for they knew he had
spoken this parable against them.
They watched him and sent out spies, who
pretended to be righteous, that they might trap
him in something he said, so as to deliver
him up to the power and authority of the governor.
They asked him, “Teacher, we know that you
say and teach what is right, and aren’t partial
to anyone, but truly teach the way of God.
Is it lawful for us to pay taxes to
Caesar, or not?”
But he perceived their craftiness, and
said to them, “Why do you test me?
Show me
a denarius.
Whose image and inscription are on it?”
They answered, “Caesar’s.”
He said to them, “Then give to Caesar the
things that are Caesar’s, and to God the things
that are God’s.”
They weren’t able to trap him in his words
before the people.
They marvelled at his answer and were
silent.
Some of the Sadducees came to him, those
who deny that there is a resurrection.
They asked him, “Teacher, Moses wrote to
us that if a man’s brother dies having a
wife, and he is childless, his brother should
take the wife and raise up children for
his brother.
There were therefore seven brothers.
The first took a wife, and died childless.
The second took her as wife, and he died
childless.
The third took her, and likewise the seven
all left no children, and died.
Afterward the woman also died.
Therefore in the resurrection whose wife
of them will she be?
For the seven had her as a wife.”
Jesus said to them, “The children of this
age marry and are given in marriage.
But those who are considered worthy to attain
to that age and the resurrection from the
dead neither marry nor are given in
marriage.
For they can’t die any more, for they are
like the angels and are children of God, being
children of the resurrection.
But that the dead are raised, even Moses
showed at the bush, when he called the Lord
‘The God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and
the God of Jacob.’
Now he is not the God of the dead, but of
the living, for all are alive to him.”
Some of the scribes answered, “Teacher,
you speak well.”
They didn’t dare to ask him any more
questions.
He said to them, “Why do they say that the
Christ is David’s son?
David himself says in the book of Psalms, ‘The
Lord said to my Lord, “Sit at my right
hand, until I make your enemies the
footstool of your feet.”’ “David therefore calls
him Lord, so how is he his son?”
In the hearing of all the people, he said
to his disciples, “Beware of those scribes
who like to walk in long robes, and
love greetings in the marketplaces, the best seats
in the synagogues, and the best places at
feasts; who devour widows’ houses, and
for a pretence make long prayers.
These will receive greater condemnation.”
Luke, chapter twenty-one.
He looked up and saw the rich people
who were putting their gifts into the treasury.
He saw a certain poor widow casting in two
small brass coins.
He said, “Truly I tell you, this poor widow
put in more than all of them, for all
these put in gifts for God from their
abundance, but she, out of her poverty, put
in all that she had to live on.”
As some were talking about the temple and
how it was decorated with beautiful stones
and gifts, he said, “As for these things
which you see, the days will come in which
there will not be left here one stone on
another that will not be thrown down.”
They asked him, “Teacher, so when will
these things be?
What is the sign that these things are
about to happen?”
He said, “Watch out that you don’t get led
astray, for many will come in my name, saying,
‘I am he,’ and, ‘The time is at hand.’
Therefore don’t follow them.
When you hear of wars and disturbances,
don’t be terrified, for these things must happen
first, but the end won’t come
immediately.”
Then he said to them, “Nation will
rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom.
There will be great earthquakes, famines,
and plagues in various places.
There will be terrors and great signs from
heaven.
But before all these things, they will lay
their hands on you and will persecute you,
delivering you up to synagogues and
prisons, bringing you before kings and governors
for my name’s sake.
It will turn out as a testimony for you.
Settle it therefore in your hearts not to
meditate beforehand how to answer, for I will
give you a mouth and wisdom which all your
adversaries will not be able to withstand
or to contradict.
You will be handed over even by parents,
brothers, relatives, and friends.
They will cause some of you to be put to
death.
You will be hated by all men for my name’s
sake.
And not a hair of your head will perish.
“By your endurance you will win your
lives.
“But when you see Jerusalem surrounded by
armies, then know that its desolation is at
hand.
Then let those who are in Judea flee to
the mountains.
Let those who are in the middle of her
depart.
Let those who are in the country not enter
therein.
For these are days of vengeance, that all
things which are written may be fulfilled.
Woe to those who are pregnant and to those
who nurse infants in those days!
For there will be great distress in the
land and wrath to this people.
They will fall by the edge of the sword,
and will be led captive into all the nations.
Jerusalem will be trampled down by the Gentiles
until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled.
“There will be signs in the sun, moon,
and stars; and on the earth anxiety of nations,
in perplexity for the roaring of the sea
and the waves; men fainting for fear and for
expectation of the things which are coming on
the world, for the powers of the heavens
will be shaken.
Then they will see the Son of Man coming
in a cloud with power and great glory.
But when these things begin to happen, look
up and lift up your heads, because your
redemption is near.”
He told them a parable.
“See the fig tree and all the trees.
When they are already budding, you see it
and know by your own selves that the summer
is already near.
Even so you also, when you see these
things happening, know that God’s Kingdom is near.
Most certainly I tell you, this generation will
not pass away until all things are accomplished.
Heaven and earth will pass away, but my
words will by no means pass away.
“So be careful, or your hearts will
be loaded down with carousing, drunkenness, and cares
of this life, and that day will come on
you suddenly.
For it will come like a snare on all those
who dwell on the surface of all the earth.
Therefore be watchful all the time, praying
that you may be counted worthy to escape
all these things that will happen, and to
stand before the Son of Man.”
Every day Jesus was teaching in the temple,
and every night he would go out and spend
the night on the mountain that is called
Olivet.
All the people came early in the morning
to him in
the temple to hear him.
Luke, chapter twenty-two.
Now the feast of unleavened bread, which
is called the Passover, was approaching.
The chief priests and the scribes sought how
they might put him to death, for they feared
the people.
Satan entered into Judas, who was also
called Iscariot, who was counted with the twelve.
He went away and talked with the chief
priests and captains about how he might deliver
him to them.
They were glad, and agreed to give him
money.
He consented and sought an opportunity to deliver
him to them in the absence of the multitude.
The day of unleavened bread came, on which
the Passover must be sacrificed.
Jesus sent Peter and John, saying, “Go and
prepare the Passover for us, that we may eat.”
They said to him, “Where do you want us to
prepare?”
He said to them, “Behold, when you have
entered into the city, a man carrying a pitcher
of water will meet you.
Follow him into the house which he enters.
Tell the master of the house, ‘The Teacher
says to you, “Where is the guest room, where
I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’
He will show you a large, furnished upper
room.
Make preparations there.”
They went, found things as Jesus had told
them, and they prepared the Passover.
When the hour had come, he sat down with
the twelve apostles.
He said to them, “I have earnestly desired
to eat this Passover with you before I suffer,
for I tell you, I will no longer by any
means eat of it until it is fulfilled in God’s
Kingdom.”
He received a cup, and when he had given
thanks, he said, “Take this and share it amongst
yourselves, for I tell you, I will not drink
at all again from the fruit of the vine,
until God’s Kingdom comes.”
He took bread, and when he had given thanks,
he broke and gave it to them, saying, “This
is my body which is given for you.
Do this in memory of me.”
Likewise, he took the cup after supper, saying,
“This cup is the new covenant in my blood,
which is poured out for you.
But behold, the hand of him who betrays me
is with me on the table.
The Son of Man indeed goes as it has
been determined, but woe to that man through whom
he is betrayed!”
They began to question amongst themselves which of
them it was who would do this thing.
A dispute also arose amongst them, which
of them was considered to be greatest.
He said to them, “The kings of the nations
lord it over them, and those who have authority
over them are called ‘benefactors.’
But not so with you.
Rather, the one who is greater amongst you,
let him become as the younger, and one
who is governing, as one who serves.
For who is greater, one who sits at the
table, or one who serves?
Isn’t it he who sits at the table?
But I am amongst you as one who serves.
“But you are those who have continued with
me in my trials.
I confer on you a kingdom, even as my
Father conferred on me, that you may eat and
drink at my table in my Kingdom.
You will sit on thrones, judging the
twelve tribes of Israel.”
The Lord said, “Simon, Simon, behold,
Satan asked to
have all of you, that he might sift you
as wheat, but I prayed for you, that your faith
wouldn’t fail.
You, when once you have turned again,
establish your brothers.”
He said to him, “Lord, I am ready to go
with you both to prison and to death!”
He said, “I tell you, Peter, the rooster
will by no means crow today until you
deny that you know me three times.”
He said to them, “When I sent you out
without purse, bag, and sandals, did you lack anything?”
They said, “Nothing.”
Then he said to them, “But now, whoever has
a purse, let him take it, and likewise a
bag.
Whoever has none, let him sell his cloak,
and buy a sword.
For I tell you that this which is written
must still be fulfilled in me: ‘He
was counted with transgressors.’
For that which concerns me is being
fulfilled.”
They said, “Lord, behold, here are two
swords.”
He said to them, “That is enough.”
He came out and went, as his custom was,
to the Mount of Olives.
His disciples also followed him.
When he was at the place, he said
to them, “Pray that you don’t enter into temptation.”
He was withdrawn from them about a stone’s
throw, and he knelt down and prayed, saying,
“Father, if you are willing, remove this
cup from me.
Nevertheless, not my will, but yours, be
done.”
An angel from heaven appeared to him,
strengthening him.
Being in agony, he prayed more earnestly.
His sweat became like great drops of blood
falling down on the ground.
When he rose up from his prayer, he
came to the disciples and found them sleeping because
of grief, and said to them, “Why do you
sleep?
Rise and pray that you may not enter into
temptation.”
While he was still speaking, a crowd
appeared.
He who was called Judas, one of the
twelve, was leading them.
He came near to Jesus to kiss him.
But Jesus said to him, “Judas, do you
betray the Son of Man with
a kiss?”
When those who were around him saw what
was about to happen, they said to him, “Lord,
shall we strike with the sword?”
A certain one of them struck the servant of
the high priest, and cut off his right ear.
But Jesus answered, “Let me at least do
this”—and he touched his ear and healed him.
Jesus said to the chief priests, captains of
the temple, and elders, who had come against
him, “Have you come out as against a
robber, with swords and clubs?
When I was with you in the temple
daily, you didn’t stretch out your hands against me.
But this is your hour, and the power of
darkness.”
They seized him and led him away, and
brought him into the high priest’s house.
But Peter followed from a distance.
When they had kindled a fire in the
middle of the courtyard and had sat down together,
Peter sat amongst them.
A certain servant girl saw him as he sat
in the light, and looking intently at him, said,
“This man also was with him.”
He denied Jesus, saying, “Woman, I don’t
know him.”
After a little while someone else saw him
and said, “You also are one of them!”
But Peter answered, “Man, I am not!”
After about one hour passed, another
confidently affirmed, saying, “Truly this man also
was with him, for he is a Galilean!”
But Peter said, “Man, I don’t know what
you are talking about!”
Immediately, while he was still speaking,
a rooster crowed.
The Lord turned and looked at Peter.
Then Peter remembered the Lord’s word, how
he said to him, “Before the rooster crows
you will deny me three times.”
He went out, and wept bitterly.
The men who held Jesus mocked him and beat
him.
Having blindfolded him, they struck him on
the face and asked him, “Prophesy!
Who is the one who struck you?”
They spoke many other things against him,
insulting him.
As soon as it was day, the assembly
of the elders of the people were gathered together,
both chief priests and scribes, and they
led him away into their council, saying, “If
you are the Christ, tell us.”
But he said to them, “If I tell you, you
won’t believe, and if I ask, you will in no
way answer me or let me go.
From now on, the Son of Man will be seated
at the right hand of the power of God.”
They all said, “Are you then the Son of
God?”
He said to them, “You say it, because I
am.”
They said, “Why do we need any more
witness?
For we ourselves have heard from his own
mouth!”
Luke, chapter twenty-three.
The whole company of them rose up and
brought him before Pilate.
They began to accuse him, saying, “We
found this man perverting the nation, forbidding
paying taxes to Caesar, and saying that he
himself is Christ, a king.”
Pilate asked him, “Are you the King of the
Jews?”
He answered him, “So you say.”
Pilate said to the chief priests and the
multitudes, “I find no basis for a charge against
this man.”
But they insisted, saying, “He stirs up
the people, teaching throughout all Judea, beginning
from Galilee even to this place.”
But when Pilate heard Galilee mentioned,
he asked if the man was a Galilean.
When he found out that he was in
Herod’s jurisdiction, he sent him to Herod, who was
also in Jerusalem during those days.
Now when Herod saw Jesus, he was exceedingly glad,
for he had wanted to see him for a
long time, because he had heard many
things about him.
He hoped to see some miracle done by him.
He questioned him with many words, but he
gave no answers.
The chief priests and the scribes stood,
vehemently accusing him.
Herod with his soldiers humiliated him and
mocked him.
Dressing him in luxurious clothing, they
sent him back to Pilate.
Herod and Pilate became friends with each other
that very day, for before that they were
enemies with each other.
Pilate called together the chief priests, the
rulers, and the people, and said to them,
“You brought this man to me as one
that perverts the people, and behold, having examined
him before you, I found no basis for
a charge against this man concerning those things
of which you accuse him.
Neither has Herod, for I sent you to him,
and see, nothing worthy of death has been done
by him.
I will therefore chastise him and release
him.”
Now he had to release one prisoner to them
at the feast.
But they all cried out together, saying,
“Away with this man!
Release to us Barabbas!”— one who was thrown
into prison for a certain revolt in the
city, and for murder.
Then Pilate spoke to them again, wanting
to release Jesus, but they shouted, saying,
“Crucify!
Crucify him!”
He said to them the third time, “Why?
What evil has this man done?
I have found no capital crime in him.
I will therefore chastise him and release
him.”
But they were urgent with loud voices,
asking that he might be crucified.
Their voices and the voices of the chief
priests prevailed.
Pilate decreed that what they asked for
should be done.
He released him who had been thrown
into prison for insurrection and murder, for whom
they asked, but he delivered Jesus up to
their will.
When they led him away, they grabbed one
Simon of Cyrene, coming from the country, and
laid the cross on him to carry it after
Jesus.
A great multitude of the people followed
him, including women who also mourned and lamented
him.
But Jesus, turning to them, said, “Daughters
of Jerusalem, don’t weep for me, but
weep for yourselves and for your children.
For behold, the days are coming in which
they will say, ‘Blessed are the barren, the
wombs that never bore, and the breasts
that never nursed.’
Then they will begin to tell the
mountains, ‘Fall on us!’
and tell the hills, ‘Cover us.’
For if they do these things in the green
tree, what will be done in the dry?”
There were also others, two criminals, led
with him to be put to death.
When they came to the place that is called
“The Skull”, they crucified him there with
the criminals, one on the right and the
other on the left.
Jesus said, “Father, forgive them, for
they don’t know what they are doing.”
Dividing his garments amongst them, they
cast lots.
The people stood watching.
The rulers with them also scoffed at him,
saying, “He saved others.
Let him save himself, if this is the
Christ of God, his chosen one!”
The soldiers also mocked him, coming to
him and offering him vinegar, and saying, “If
you are the King of the Jews, save
yourself!”
An inscription was also written over him
in letters of Greek, Latin, and Hebrew: “THIS
IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.”
One of the criminals who was hanged insulted
him, saying, “If you are the Christ, save
yourself and us!”
But the other answered, and rebuking him
said, “Don’t you even fear God, seeing
you are under the same condemnation?
And we indeed justly, for we receive the
due reward for our deeds, but this man
has done nothing wrong.”
He said to Jesus, “Lord, remember me when
you come into your Kingdom.”
Jesus said to him, “Assuredly I tell you,
today you will be with me in Paradise.”
It was now about the sixth hour, and
darkness came over the whole land until the ninth
hour.
The sun was darkened, and the veil of the
temple was torn in two.
Jesus, crying with a loud voice, said,
“Father, into your hands I commit my spirit!”
Having said this, he breathed his last.
When the centurion saw what was done, he
glorified God, saying, “Certainly this was
a righteous man.”
All the multitudes that came together to see
this, when they saw the things that were
done, returned home beating their breasts.
All his acquaintances and the women who followed
with him from Galilee stood at a distance,
watching these things.
Behold, there was a man named Joseph, who was
a member of the council, a good and righteous
man (he had not consented to their counsel
and deed), from Arimathaea, a city of
the Jews, who was also waiting for God’s
Kingdom.
This man went to Pilate, and asked for
Jesus’ body.
He took it down and wrapped it in a linen
cloth, and laid him in a tomb that was cut
in stone, where no one had ever been laid.
It was the day of the Preparation, and the
Sabbath was drawing near.
The women who had come with him out of
Galilee followed after, and saw the tomb and how
his body was laid.
They returned and prepared spices and
ointments.
On the Sabbath they rested according to
the commandment.
Luke, chapter twenty-four.
But on the first day of the week, at
early dawn, they and some others came to the tomb,
bringing the spices which they had
prepared.
They found the stone rolled away from the
tomb.
They entered in, and didn’t find the Lord
Jesus’ body.
While they were greatly perplexed about this,
behold, two men stood by them in dazzling
clothing.
Becoming terrified, they bowed their faces
down to the earth.
The men said to them, “Why do you seek the
living amongst the dead?
He isn’t here, but is risen.
Remember what he told you when he was still
in Galilee, saying that the Son of Man must
be delivered up into the hands of sinful
men and be crucified, and the third day rise
again?”
They remembered his words, returned from the tomb,
and told all these things to the eleven
and to all the rest.
Now they were Mary Magdalene, Joanna, and
Mary the mother of James.
The other women with them told these
things to the apostles.
These words seemed to them to be nonsense,
and they didn’t believe them.
But Peter got up and ran to the tomb.
Stooping and looking in, he saw the strips
of linen lying by themselves, and he departed
to his home, wondering what had happened.
Behold, two of them were going that very
day to a village named Emmaus, which was sixty
stadia from Jerusalem.
They talked with each other about all of
these things which had happened.
While they talked and questioned together, Jesus
himself came near, and went with them.
But their eyes were kept from recognising
him.
He said to them, “What are you talking
about as you walk, and are sad?”
One of them, named Cleopas, answered him,
“Are you the only stranger in Jerusalem who
doesn’t know the things which have
happened there in these days?”
He said to them, “What things?”
They said to him, “The things concerning
Jesus the Nazarene, who was a prophet mighty
in deed and word before God and all the
people; and how the chief priests and our rulers
delivered him up to be condemned to death,
and crucified him.
But we were hoping that it was he who
would redeem Israel.
Yes, and besides all this, it is now the
third day since these things happened.
Also, certain women of our company amazed
us, having arrived early at the tomb; and
when they didn’t find his body, they came
saying that they had also seen a vision of
angels, who said that he was alive.
Some of us went to the tomb and found
it just like the women had said, but they didn’t
see him.”
He said to them, “Foolish people, and slow
of heart to believe in all that the prophets
have spoken!
Didn’t the Christ have to suffer these
things and to enter into his glory?”
Beginning from Moses and from all the prophets,
he explained to them in all the Scriptures
the things concerning himself.
They came near to the village where they were
going, and he acted like he would go further.
They urged him, saying, “Stay with us, for
it is almost evening, and the day is almost
over.”
He went in to stay with them.
When he had sat down at the table with
them, he took the bread and gave thanks.
Breaking it, he gave it to them.
Their eyes were opened and they recognised
him; then he vanished out of their sight.
They said to one another, “Weren’t our hearts
burning within us while he spoke to us
along the way, and while he opened the
Scriptures to us?”
They rose up that very hour, returned
to Jerusalem, and found the eleven gathered together,
and those who were with them, saying, “The
Lord is risen indeed, and has appeared to
Simon!”
They related the things that happened along the
way, and how he was recognised by them
in the breaking of the bread.
As they said these things, Jesus himself
stood amongst them, and said to them, “Peace
be to you.”
But they were terrified and filled with fear,
and supposed that they had seen a spirit.
He said to them, “Why are you troubled?
Why do doubts arise in your hearts?
See my hands and my feet, that it is truly
me.
Touch me and see, for a spirit doesn’t
have flesh and bones, as you see that
I have.”
When he had said this, he showed them his
hands and his feet.
While they still didn’t believe for joy, and
wondered, he said to them, “Do you have
anything here to eat?”
They gave him a piece of a broiled fish
and some honeycomb.
He took them, and ate in front of them.
He said to them, “This is what I told
you while I was still with you, that all things
which are written in the law of Moses,
the prophets, and the psalms concerning me must
be fulfilled.”
Then he opened their minds, that they
might understand the Scriptures.
He said to them, “Thus it is written, and
thus it was necessary for the Christ to suffer
and to rise from the dead the third
day, and that repentance and remission of sins should
be preached in his name to all the
nations, beginning at Jerusalem.
You are witnesses of these things.
Behold, I send out the promise of my
Father on you.
But wait in the city of Jerusalem until
you are clothed with power from on high.”
He led them out as far as Bethany, and he
lifted up his hands and blessed them.
While he blessed them, he withdrew from
them and was carried up into heaven.
They worshipped him and returned to Jerusalem
with great joy, and were continually in
the temple, praising and blessing God.
Amen.
Ecclesiastes, chapter one.
The words of the Preacher, the son of
David, king in Jerusalem: “Vanity of
vanities,” says the Preacher; “Vanity of
vanities, all is vanity.”
What does man gain from all his labour in
which he labours under the sun?
One generation goes, and another generation
comes; but the earth remains forever.
The sun also rises, and the sun goes down,
and hurries to its place where it rises.
The wind goes towards the south, and turns
around to the north.
It turns around continually as it goes,
and the wind returns again to its courses.
All the rivers run into the sea, yet the
sea is not full.
To the place where the rivers flow, there
they flow again.
All things are full of weariness beyond
uttering.
The eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor
the ear filled with hearing.
That which has been is that which
shall be, and that which has been done is
that which shall be done; and there is no new
thing under the sun.
Is there a thing of which it may be said,
“Behold, this is new?”
It has been long ago, in the ages which
were before us.
There is no memory of the former; neither
shall there be any memory of the latter that
are to come, amongst those that shall come
after.
I, the Preacher, was king over Israel in
Jerusalem.
I applied my heart to seek and to search
out by wisdom concerning all that is done under
the sky.
It is a heavy burden that God has given to
the sons of men to be afflicted with.
I have seen all the works that are done
under the sun; and behold, all is vanity and
a chasing after wind.
That which is crooked can’t be made straight;
and that which is lacking can’t be counted.
I said to myself, “Behold, I have obtained
for myself great wisdom above all who were
before me in Jerusalem.
Yes, my heart has had great experience of
wisdom and knowledge.”
I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to
know madness and folly.
I perceived that this also was a chasing
after wind.
For in much wisdom is much grief; and he
who increases knowledge increases sorrow.
Ecclesiastes, chapter two.
I said in my heart, “Come now, I will test
you with mirth; therefore enjoy pleasure;”
and behold, this also was vanity.
I said of laughter, “It is foolishness;”
and of mirth, “What does it accomplish?”
I searched in my heart how to cheer my
flesh with wine, my heart yet guiding me with
wisdom, and how to lay hold of folly, until
I might see what it was good for the sons
of men that they should do under heaven
all the days of their lives.
I made myself great works.
I built myself houses.
I planted myself vineyards.
I made myself gardens and parks, and I
planted trees in them of all kinds of fruit.
I made myself pools of water, to water the
forest where trees were grown.
I bought male servants and female servants,
and had servants born in my house.
I also had great possessions of herds and
flocks, above all who were before me in Jerusalem.
I also gathered silver and gold for myself,
and the treasure of kings and of the provinces.
I got myself male and female singers, and
the delights of the sons of men: musical instruments
of all sorts.
So I was great, and increased more than
all who were before me in Jerusalem.
My wisdom also remained with me.
Whatever my eyes desired, I didn’t keep
from them.
I didn’t withhold my heart from any joy,
for my heart rejoiced because of all my labour,
and this was my portion from all my
labour.
Then I looked at all the works that my
hands had worked, and at the labour that I had
laboured to do; and behold, all was vanity
and a chasing after wind, and
there was no profit under the sun.
I turned myself to consider wisdom, madness,
and folly; for what can the king’s successor
do?
Just that which has been done long ago.
Then I saw that wisdom excels folly, as
far as light excels darkness.
The wise man’s eyes are in his head,
and the fool walks in darkness—and yet I perceived
that one event happens to them all.
Then I said in my heart, “As it happens to
the fool, so will it happen even to me; and
why was I then more wise?”
Then I said in my heart that this also is
vanity.
For of the wise man, even as of the fool,
there is no memory forever, since
in the days to come all will have been
long forgotten.
Indeed, the wise man must die just like
the fool!
So I hated life, because the work that is
worked under the sun was grievous to me; for
all is vanity and a chasing after wind.
I hated all my labour in which I laboured
under the sun, because I must leave
it to the man who comes after me.
Who knows whether he will be a wise man or
a fool?
Yet he will have rule over all of my
labour in which I have laboured, and in which I
have shown myself wise under the sun.
This also is vanity.
Therefore I began to cause my heart to
despair concerning all the labour in which I had
laboured under the sun.
For there is a man whose labour
is with wisdom, with knowledge, and with skilfulness;
yet he shall leave it for his portion to a
man who has not laboured for it.
This also is vanity and a great evil.
For what does a man have of all his labour
and of the striving of his heart, in which
he labours under the sun?
For all his days are sorrows, and his
travail is grief; yes, even in the night
his heart takes no rest.
This also is vanity.
There is nothing better for a man than that
he should eat and drink, and make his soul
enjoy good in his labour.
This also I saw, that it is from the hand
of God.
For who can eat, or who can have
enjoyment, more than I?
For to the man who pleases him, God
gives wisdom, knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner
he gives travail, to gather and to heap up,
that he may give to him who pleases God.
This also is vanity and a chasing after
wind.
Ecclesiastes, chapter three.
For everything there is a season, and a
time for every purpose under heaven: a time
to be born, and a time to die; a time
to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is
planted; a time to kill, and a time to
heal; a time to break down, and a
time to build up; a time to weep, and a
time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time
to dance; a time to cast away stones, and
a time to gather stones together; a
time to embrace, and a time to refrain from
embracing; a time to seek, and a time to
lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast
away; a time to tear, and a time to sew;
a time to keep silence, and a time to speak;
a time to love, and a time to hate; a
time for war, and a time for peace.
What profit has he who works in that in
which he labours?
I have seen the burden which God has given
to the sons of men to be afflicted with.
He has made everything beautiful in its
time.
He has also set eternity in their hearts, yet
so that man can’t find out the work that
God has done from the beginning even to
the end.
I know that there is nothing better for them
than to rejoice, and to do good as long
as they live.
Also that every man should eat and drink, and
enjoy good in all his labour, is the gift
of God.
I know that whatever God does, it shall be
forever.
Nothing can be added to it, nor anything taken
from it; and God has done it, that men
should fear before him.
That which is has been long ago, and that
which is to be has been long ago.
God seeks again that which is passed away.
Moreover I saw under the sun, in the place
of justice, that wickedness was there; and
in the place of righteousness, that
wickedness was there.
I said in my heart, “God will judge the
righteous and the wicked; for there is a time
there for every purpose and for every
work.”
I said in my heart, “As for the sons of
men, God tests them, so that they may see
that they themselves are like animals.
For that which happens to the sons of men
happens to animals.
Even one thing happens to them.
As the one dies, so the other dies.
Yes, they have all one breath; and man has
no advantage over the animals, for
all is vanity.
All go to one place.
All are from the dust, and all turn to
dust again.
Who knows the spirit of man, whether it
goes upward, and the spirit of the animal, whether
it goes downward to the earth?”
Therefore I saw that there is nothing better
than that a man should rejoice in his works,
for that is his portion; for who can bring
him to see what will be after him?
Ecclesiastes, chapter four.
Then I returned and saw all the oppressions
that are done under the sun: and behold,
the tears of those who were oppressed, and
they had no comforter; and on the side of
their oppressors there was power; but they
had no comforter.
Therefore I praised the dead who have been
long dead more than the living who are yet
alive.
Yes, better than them both is him who has
not yet been, who has not seen the evil
work that is done under the sun.
Then I saw all the labour and achievement
that is the envy of a man’s neighbour.
This also is vanity and a striving after
wind.
The fool folds his hands together and
ruins himself.
Better is a handful, with quietness, than
two handfuls with labour and chasing after
wind.
Then I returned and saw vanity under the
sun.
There is one who is alone, and he has
neither son nor brother.
There is no end to all of his
labour, neither are his eyes satisfied with wealth.
“For whom then do I labour and deprive my
soul of enjoyment?”
This also is vanity.
Yes, it is a miserable business.
Two are better than one, because they have
a good reward for their labour.
For if they fall, the one will lift up his
fellow; but woe to him who is alone when he
falls, and doesn’t have another to lift
him up.
Again, if two lie together, then they have
warmth; but how can one keep warm alone?
If a man prevails against one who is
alone, two shall withstand him; and
a threefold cord is not quickly broken.
Better is a poor and wise youth than an
old and foolish king who doesn’t know how to
receive admonition any more.
For out of prison he came out to be king;
yes, even in his kingdom he was born poor.
I saw all the living who walk under the
sun, that they were with the youth, the other,
who succeeded him.
There was no end of all the people, even
of all them over whom he was—yet those who
come after shall not rejoice in him.
Surely this also is vanity and a chasing
after wind.
Ecclesiastes, chapter five.
Guard your steps when you go to God’s house;
for to draw near to listen is better than
to give the sacrifice of fools, for they
don’t know that they do evil.
Don’t be rash with your mouth, and don’t
let your heart be hasty to utter anything before
God; for God is in heaven, and you on
earth.
Therefore let your words be few.
For as a dream comes with a multitude of
cares, so a fool’s speech with a multitude of
words.
When you vow a vow to God, don’t defer to
pay it; for he has no pleasure in fools.
Pay that which you vow.
It is better that you should not vow, than
that you should vow and not pay.
Don’t allow your mouth to lead you into
sin.
Don’t protest before the messenger that
this was a mistake.
Why should God be angry at your voice, and
destroy the work of your hands?
For in the multitude of dreams there are
vanities, as well as in many words; but you
must fear God.
If you see the oppression of the poor,
and the violent taking away of justice and righteousness
in a district, don’t marvel at the matter,
for one official is eyed by a higher one,
and there are officials over them.
Moreover the profit of the earth is for
all.
The king profits from the field.
He who loves silver shall not be satisfied
with silver, nor he who loves abundance, with
increase.
This also is vanity.
When goods increase, those who eat them
are increased; and what advantage is there to
its owner, except to feast on them with
his eyes?
The sleep of a labouring man is sweet,
whether he eats little or much; but the abundance
of the rich will not allow him to sleep.
There is a grievous evil which I have seen
under the sun: wealth kept by its owner to
his harm.
Those riches perish by misfortune, and if
he has fathered a son, there is nothing in
his hand.
As he came out of his mother’s womb, naked
shall he go again as he came, and shall take
nothing for his labour, which he may carry
away in his hand.
This also is a grievous evil, that in all
points as he came, so shall he go.
And what profit does he have who labours
for the wind?
All his days he also eats in darkness, he
is frustrated, and has sickness and wrath.
Behold, that which I have seen to be good
and proper is for one to eat and to drink,
and to enjoy good in all his labour, in
which he labours under the sun, all the days
of his life which God has given him; for
this is his portion.
Every man also to whom God has given riches
and wealth, and has given him power to eat
of it, and to take his portion, and to
rejoice in his labour—this is the gift of God.
For he shall not often reflect on the days
of his life, because God occupies him with
the joy of his heart.
Ecclesiastes, chapter six.
There is an evil which I have seen under the
sun, and it is heavy on men: a man to whom
God gives riches, wealth, and honour, so that
he lacks nothing for his soul of all that
he desires, yet God gives him no power to
eat of it, but an alien eats it.
This is vanity, and it is an evil disease.
If a man fathers a hundred children, and lives
many years, so that the days of his years
are many, but his soul is not filled with
good, and moreover he has no burial, I
say that a stillborn child is better than
he; for it comes in vanity, and departs in
darkness, and its name is covered with
darkness.
Moreover it has not seen the sun nor known
it.
This has rest rather than the other.
Yes, though he live a thousand years twice
told, and yet fails to enjoy good, don’t
all go to one place?
All the labour of man is for his mouth,
and yet the appetite is not filled.
For what advantage has the wise more than
the fool?
What has the poor man, that knows how to
walk before the living?
Better is the sight of the eyes than the
wandering of the desire.
This also is vanity and a chasing after
wind.
Whatever has been, its name was given long
ago; and it is known what man is;
neither can he contend with him who is
mightier than he.
For there are many words that create
vanity.
What does that profit man?
For who knows what is good for man in life,
all the days of his vain life which he spends
like a shadow?
For who can tell a man what will be after
him under the sun?
Ecclesiastes, chapter seven.
A good name is better than fine perfume; and
the day of death better than the day of
one’s birth.
It is better to go to the house of
mourning than to go to the house of feasting; for
that is the end of all men, and the living
should take this to heart.
Sorrow is better than laughter; for by the
sadness of the face the heart is made good.
The heart of the wise is in the house of
mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house
of mirth.
It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise
than for a man to hear the song of fools.
For as the crackling of thorns under a
pot, so is the laughter of the fool.
This also is vanity.
Surely extortion makes the wise man
foolish; and a bribe destroys the understanding.
Better is the end of a thing than its
beginning.
The patient in spirit is better than the
proud in spirit.
Don’t be hasty in your spirit to be angry,
for anger rests in the bosom of fools.
Don’t say, “Why were the former days
better than these?”
For you do not ask wisely about this.
Wisdom is as good as an inheritance.
Yes, it is more excellent for those who
see the sun.
For wisdom is a defence, even as money is
a defence; but the excellency of knowledge
is that wisdom preserves the life of him
who has it.
Consider the work of God, for who can make
that straight which he has made crooked?
In the day of prosperity be joyful, and in
the day of adversity consider; yes,
God has made the one side by side with the
other, to the end that man should not find
out anything after him.
All this I have seen in my days of
vanity: there is a righteous man who perishes in his
righteousness, and there is a wicked man
who lives long in his evildoing.
Don’t be overly righteous, neither make
yourself overly wise.
Why should you destroy yourself?
Don’t be too wicked, neither be foolish.
Why should you die before your time?
It is good that you should take hold of
this.
Yes, also don’t withdraw your hand from that;
for he who fears God will come out of
them all.
Wisdom is a strength to the wise man more
than ten rulers who are in a city.
Surely there is not a righteous man on
earth who does good and doesn’t sin.
Also don’t take heed to all words that
are spoken, lest you hear your servant curse you;
for often your own heart knows that you
yourself have likewise cursed others.
All this I have proved in wisdom.
I said, “I will be wise;” but it was far
from me.
That which is, is far off and exceedingly
deep.
Who can find it out?
I turned around, and my heart sought to know
and to search out, and to seek wisdom and
the scheme of things, and to know
that wickedness is stupidity, and that foolishness
is madness.
I find more bitter than death the woman
whose heart is snares and traps, whose hands
are chains.
Whoever pleases God shall escape from her;
but the sinner will be ensnared by her.
“Behold, I have found this,” says the
Preacher, “to one another, to find an explanation
which my soul still seeks, but I have not
found.
I have found one man amongst a thousand, but
I have not found a woman amongst all those.
Behold, I have only found this: that God
made mankind upright; but they search
for many inventions.”
Ecclesiastes, chapter eight.
Who is like the wise man?
And who knows the interpretation of a
thing?
A man’s wisdom makes his face shine, and
the hardness of his face is changed.
I say, “Keep the king’s command!”
because of the oath to God.
Don’t be hasty to go out of his presence.
Don’t persist in an evil thing, for he
does whatever pleases him, for the king’s word
is supreme.
Who can say to him, “What are you doing?”
Whoever keeps the commandment shall not come to
harm, and his wise heart will know the
time and procedure.
For there is a time and procedure for
every purpose, although the misery of man is heavy
on him.
For he doesn’t know that which will be;
for who can tell him how it will be?
There is no man who has power over
the spirit to contain the spirit; neither does he
have power over the day of death.
There is no discharge in war; neither
shall wickedness deliver those who practise it.
All this I have seen, and applied my mind
to every work that is done under the sun.
There is a time in which one man has power
over another to his hurt.
So I saw the wicked buried.
Indeed they came also from holiness.
They went and were forgotten in the city
where they did this.
This also is vanity.
Because sentence against an evil work is
not executed speedily, therefore the heart of
the sons of men is fully set in them to do
evil.
Though a sinner commits crimes a hundred times,
and lives long, yet surely I know that
it will be better with those who fear God,
who are reverent before him.
But it shall not be well with the
wicked, neither shall he lengthen days like a shadow,
because he doesn’t fear God.
There is a vanity which is done on the
earth, that there are righteous men to whom it
happens according to the work of the
wicked.
Again, there are wicked men to whom it
happens according to the work of the righteous.
I said that this also is vanity.
Then I commended mirth, because a man has
no better thing under the sun than to eat,
to drink, and to be joyful: for that will
accompany him in his labour all the days of
his life which God has given him under the
sun.
When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and
to see the business that is done on the earth
(even though eyes see no sleep day or night),
then I saw all the work of God, that
man can’t find out the work that is done
under the sun, because however much a man labours
to seek it out, yet he won’t find it.
Yes even though a wise man thinks he can
comprehend it, he won’t be able to find it.
Ecclesiastes, chapter nine.
For all this I laid to my heart, even to
explore all this: that the righteous, and
the wise, and their works, are in the hand
of God; whether it is love or hatred, man
doesn’t know it; all is before them.
All things come alike to all.
There is one event to the righteous and to
the wicked; to the good, to the clean, to
the unclean, to him who sacrifices, and to
him who doesn’t sacrifice.
As is the good, so is the sinner; he who
takes an oath, as he who fears an
oath.
This is an evil in all that is done under
the sun, that there is one event to all.
Yes also, the heart of the sons of men
is full of evil, and madness is in their heart
while they live, and after that they go to
the dead.
For to him who is joined with all the
living there is hope; for a living dog is better
than a dead lion.
For the living know that they will die,
but the dead don’t know anything, neither do
they have any more a reward; for their
memory is forgotten.
Also their love, their hatred, and their
envy has perished long ago; neither do they
any longer have a portion forever in
anything that is done under the sun.
Go your way—eat your bread with joy, and
drink your wine with a merry heart; for
God has already accepted your works.
Let your garments be always white, and
don’t let your head lack oil.
Live joyfully with the wife whom you love
all the days of your life of vanity, which
he has given you under the sun, all your
days of vanity, for that is your portion in
life, and in your labour in which you
labour under the sun.
Whatever your hand finds to do, do it with
your might; for there is no work, nor plan,
nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in Sheol, where
you are going.
I returned and saw under the sun that the
race is not to the swift, nor the battle
to the strong, neither yet bread to the
wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding,
nor yet favour to men of skill; but time
and chance happen to them all.
For man also doesn’t know his time.
As the fish that are taken in an evil net,
and as the birds that are caught in the snare,
even so are the sons of men snared in an
evil time, when it falls suddenly on them.
I have also seen wisdom under the sun in
this way, and it seemed great to me.
There was a little city, and few men within
it; and a great king came against it, besieged
it, and built great bulwarks against it.
Now a poor wise man was found in it, and
he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet
no man remembered that same poor man.
Then I said, “Wisdom is better than
strength.”
Nevertheless the poor man’s wisdom is
despised, and his words are not heard.
The words of the wise heard in quiet are
better than the cry of him who rules amongst
fools.
Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but
one sinner destroys much good.
Ecclesiastes, chapter ten.
Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer to
produce an evil odour; so does a little folly
outweigh wisdom and honour.
A wise man’s heart is at his right hand,
but a fool’s heart at his left.
Yes also when the fool walks by the
way, his understanding fails him, and he says to
everyone that he is a fool.
If the spirit of the ruler rises up
against you, don’t leave your place; for gentleness
lays great offences to rest.
There is an evil which I have seen under
the sun, the sort of error which proceeds from
the ruler.
Folly is set in
great dignity, and the rich sit in a low
place.
I have seen servants on horses, and
princes walking like servants on the earth.
He who digs a pit may fall into it;
and whoever breaks through a wall may be bitten by
a snake.
Whoever carves out stones may be injured
by them.
Whoever splits wood may be endangered by
it.
If the axe is blunt, and one doesn’t
sharpen the edge, then he must use more strength;
but skill brings success.
If the snake bites before it is charmed,
then is there no profit for the charmer’s tongue.
The words of a wise man’s mouth are gracious;
but a fool is swallowed by his own lips.
The beginning of the words of his mouth is
foolishness; and the end of his talk is mischievous
madness.
A fool also multiplies words.
Man doesn’t know what will be; and that
which will be after him, who can tell him?
The labour of fools wearies every one of them;
for he doesn’t know how to go to the city.
Woe to you, land, when your king is
a child, and your princes eat in the morning!
Happy are you, land, when your king is the
son of nobles, and your princes eat in due
season, for strength, and not for
drunkenness!
By slothfulness the roof sinks in; and
through idleness of the hands the house leaks.
A feast is made for laughter, and wine
makes the life glad; and money is
the answer for all things.
Don’t curse the king, no, not in your
thoughts; and don’t curse the rich in your bedroom,
for a bird of the sky may carry your
voice, and that which has wings may tell the matter.
Ecclesiastes, chapter eleven.
Cast your bread on the waters; for you
shall find it after many days.
Give a portion to seven, yes, even to
eight; for you don’t know what evil will
be on the earth.
If the clouds are full of rain, they empty
themselves on the earth; and if a tree falls
towards the south, or towards the north, in
the place where the tree falls, there shall
it be.
He who observes the wind won’t sow; and he
who regards the clouds won’t reap.
As you don’t know what is the way of the
wind, nor how the bones grow in the womb of
her who is with child; even so you don’t
know the work of God who does all.
In the morning sow your seed, and in
the evening don’t withhold your hand; for you don’t
know which will prosper, whether this or that,
or whether they both will be equally good.
Truly the light is sweet, and it is a
pleasant thing for the eyes to see the sun.
Yes, if a man lives many years, let him
rejoice in them all; but let him remember
the days of darkness, for they shall be
many.
All that comes is vanity.
Rejoice, young man, in your youth, and let your
heart cheer you in the days of your youth,
and walk in the ways of your heart, and in
the sight of your eyes; but know that for
all these things God will bring you into
judgement.
Therefore remove sorrow from your heart,
and put away evil from your flesh; for
youth and the dawn of life are vanity.
Ecclesiastes, chapter twelve.
Remember also your Creator in the days of
your youth, before the evil days come, and
the years draw near, when you will say, “I
have no pleasure in them;” Before the sun,
the light, the moon, and the stars are
darkened, and the clouds return after the rain;
in the day when the keepers of the
house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow
themselves, and the grinders cease because they are
few, and those who look out of the
windows are darkened, and the doors shall be
shut in the street; when the sound of the
grinding is low, and one shall rise up at
the voice of a bird, and all the daughters
of music shall be brought low; yes, they
shall be afraid of heights, and terrors
will be on the way; and the almond
tree shall blossom, and the grasshopper shall be a
burden, and desire shall fail; because man
goes to his everlasting home, and
the mourners go about the streets; before the
silver cord is severed, or the golden bowl
is broken, or the pitcher is broken at
the spring, or the wheel broken at the cistern,
and the dust returns to the earth as it
was, and the spirit returns to God who gave it.
“Vanity of vanities,” says the Preacher.
“All is vanity!”
Further, because the Preacher was wise, he
still taught the people knowledge.
Yes, he pondered, sought out, and set in
order many proverbs.
The Preacher sought to find out acceptable
words, and that which was written blamelessly,
words of truth.
The words of the wise are like goads;
and like nails well fastened are words from the
masters of assemblies, which are given
from one shepherd.
Furthermore, my son, be admonished: of
making many books there is no end; and
much study is a weariness of the flesh.
This is the end of the matter.
All has been heard.
Fear God and keep his commandments; for
this is the whole duty of man.
For God will bring every work into
judgement, with every hidden thing, whether it is
good, or whether it is evil.